<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hermes theologus, or, A divine Mercurie dispatcht with a grave message of new descants upon old records no lesse delightfull in the best sense, then truly usefull for these times / by Theoph. Wodenote ...</title>
            <author>Wodenote, Theophilus, d. 1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66817</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3242</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38728</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17948243</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17948243</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106771</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66817)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106771)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1112:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hermes theologus, or, A divine Mercurie dispatcht with a grave message of new descants upon old records no lesse delightfull in the best sense, then truly usefull for these times / by Theoph. Wodenote ...</title>
                  <author>Wodenote, Theophilus, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 154, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Royston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Added engraved t.p.</note>
                  <note>Running title: New descants upon old records.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>HERMES-THEOLOGUS or New Deſcants <hi>upon</hi> OLD RECORDS</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Rom:</hi> 2 22.</bibl> 
                     <hi>thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> abhorrest Idols, dost thou commit Sacriledge?</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>Rom. 10.12 The new Testa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment</p>
                  <p>Gen. 17.9 The old Testa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment</p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>The Chriſtian <hi>Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>6. 24.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <p>The Iewe <hi>Isa. 29. 10.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <p>The Turke <hi>in Math. 24. 5. 24.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <p>The Pagan <hi>Pſal. 7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 11.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
                  <figDesc>engraved title page</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Hermes Theologus:</hi> OR, A Divine MERCURIE Diſpatcht with a grave Meſſage <hi>OF</hi> NEW DESCANTS <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PON</hi> OLD RECORDS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No leſſe delightfull in the beſt ſenſe, then truly uſefull for theſe Times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By THEOPH: WODENOTE, <hi>B. D. ſometime fellow of</hi> Kings Colledge <hi>in</hi> CAMBRIDGE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for R. ROYSTON, 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE To the Readers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Readers,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe inſuing <hi>meditations,</hi> ſo well fitted, ſo pathetically pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſo rightly applied, to the preſent temper of theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy times, need no <hi>Preface</hi> to make way for them unto your <hi>friendly acceptance,</hi> (if there be in your breaſts, any true remaines of Conſcience or candour) nor yet <hi>any letters of commendation,</hi> to ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate their <hi>Author</hi> into your <hi>good opinions; they</hi> alone do fully declare him <hi>a Scribe inſtructed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdome of God,</hi> who <hi>like a good houſholder</hi> (as you may here find) <hi>brings forth out of his Treaſure things new and old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my reading <hi>them,</hi> together with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of <hi>him,</hi> and his preſent condition, gives occaſion (and I hope without offence) to breathe forth the <hi>paſſions</hi> of a grieving ſpirit, that mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth daily, for the deſolations of Chriſts <hi>Vineyard</hi> here amongst us, by the violent and cruell ejection
<pb facs="tcp:106771:4"/>of thoſe faithfull and skilfull <hi>husband-men,</hi> whom he had inabled and imployed to dreſſe and till the ſame; of which number this truely Reverend and Godly <hi>Author</hi> was one, whoſe name and face perhaps is ſtrange in theſe more publick and active parts of the Kingdome; but that you may the better know him, be pleaſed to underſtand, that he is a man of <hi>Iſaacs</hi> ſpirit, one of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighties inward acquaintance, that converſeth oft in ſecret with him, and hath skill to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template on things that are high.</p>
            <p>And as moſt ſutable to ſo Divine a worke, he made choice of a private life, with violence thereby unto his owne Iuſtre, his true worth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining the affectation of popular applauſe, or to make a noiſe in the world as many do, whoſe fame is beſt a far off, where themſelves are leaſt known: he was planted long ago in a remote part of this Kingdome, where for above <hi>thirty</hi> years (being <hi>Batchelour in Divinity</hi> of Antient ſtanding) he hath continued, acting the part of a faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, ruling his flock with great prudence and diſcretion, and feeding them with the food of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which he moſt skilfully dreſſed, and <hi>rightly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided,</hi> confining and applying himſelf within his proper ſphear, unto his owne people; amongst whom <hi>he was a burning and a ſhining light:</hi> and they (as they had cauſe) <hi>did rejoyce in his light,</hi> they ſat under his Miniſtry with great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
<pb facs="tcp:106771:4"/>and his Doctrine <hi>was ſweet unto them;</hi> they were in his heart, and he in theirs, to live, to die, and go to heaven together.</p>
            <p>But when they that act as if they were borne to breake in ſunder what God hath joyned, had ſet up their banners in thoſe quarters, and begun their new-found Reformation in thoſe parts, a moſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull ſeparation was quickly made between this Godly Paſtor and his loving flock, for he being throughly guilty of the ſcandals of theſe times (<hi>ſcil.</hi> of Learning, piety, wiſdome, Loyalty, obedience, honeſty, and ſuch like) and ſo not capable to be an Apoſtate from the Goſpel he had taught, was thought fit for that cauſe, <hi>to be caſt aſide as a broken ſheard,</hi> or a thing of no uſe in theſe daies, of new lights and revelations: and ſo was <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpended</hi> from his labours, <hi>ſilenced</hi> from Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and <hi>Sequeſtred</hi> from his Living, to the end that he and his flock as they had lived long moſt comfortably together, might now at the laſt even periſh and ſtarve together, he for want of Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall food, and they for want of Spirituall.</p>
            <p>But behold from that evill of theirs, good is ſprung up to us; from the <hi>darke</hi> condition of that particular Pariſh, the World in generall hath gained <hi>light;</hi> we that are a far off, had not been acquainted with his <hi>graces,</hi> if we had not been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friended by his Afflictions; the ſavour of his <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> had never reached our <hi>ſences</hi> at ſo great a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb facs="tcp:106771:5"/>(his humility did ſo hinder) had they not been thus bruiſed and beaten.</p>
            <p>This grave and good man being accuſtomed all his daies to take paines in Gods Vineyard, had not learn'd to ſtand idle, nor can his Aged years be perſwaded to it, though he be knockt off from his holy calling. He cannot ſleep, his gray haires can take no reſt, but near unto, if not within the houſe of God, though he be baniſh'd from the Temple, yet he muſt <hi>looke towards it,</hi> though charged to publiſh Chriſt no more in the Congregation, nor <hi>to Preach any longer that name,</hi> yet the word of truth being <hi>like fire within him,</hi> his ſpirit cannot reſt, nor can he forbeare, but the <hi>Preſſe</hi> muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſomething of him, if the <hi>Pulpit</hi> doth exclude him.</p>
            <p>For indeed the <hi>fire of the Sanctuary</hi> in a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſoule can never be extinguiſh'd; nor can he that doth Gods worke for Gods ſake ever be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, with all that Earth or Hell can do; the <hi>love of Chriſt</hi> is more powerfull with him to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine</hi> unto, then the <hi>threats</hi> of men or Devils can be to <hi>affright</hi> from. <hi>I muſt worke</hi> (ſaies ſuch a one) <hi>the workes of him that ſent me while it is day, the night of death will come when I cannot worke, as long as I am in the world,</hi> I muſt be a <hi>light</hi> therein, and hold forth ſome <hi>light</hi> to it, a neceſſity lies upon me ſo to do, and <hi>woe unto me if I Preach not,</hi> if I reprove
<pb facs="tcp:106771:5"/>not, if I detect not the worlds ſin, one way or other, <hi>ſcriptis ſaltem, ſi non dictis,</hi> by writing at leaſt if not by Preaching. I muſt diſcharge a good conſcience, elſe how ſhall I appeare before my Judge, at the reckoning day?</p>
            <p>Theſe, or ſuch like, are the inward diſcourſes of an honeſt heart; and theſe doubtleſſe are the reſolves of this Reverend man; who hath here ſent us from the <hi>Spirituall Garden</hi> of his ſoul, a <hi>Taſte</hi> of divine fruit, which we hope is but an <hi>Eſſay</hi> to a larger <hi>Banquet,</hi> but a glimpſe of <hi>Ophir where Gold is,</hi> of a rich mine where pretious Treaſures are to be found.</p>
            <p>And moſt worthy are theſe his Meditations our ſerious view, and friendlieſt acceptation, for the reſemblance they have and bear (which is in ſpeciall to be noted) with that forme and manner of ſpeaking uſed by our Saviour: ſure the lookes and language of this Author plainly ſhew whoſe <hi>Diſciple</hi> he is, and of <hi>what ſpirit:</hi> Tis ſaid of Chriſt, that <hi>he taught the people by parables, and without a parable ſpake he not unto them;</hi> and may not the ſame be affirmed of this man, that he teacheth us by <hi>Parables,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an <hi>Hiſtory</hi> or <hi>Similitude</hi> he ſpeaketh not? yea, as Chriſt took occaſion from every thing that occurred to raiſe ſome diſcourſe for the benefit of his hearers, ſo doth he here; with great wiſdome and truth fitly applying all particulars to the men
<pb facs="tcp:106771:6"/>and preſent conditions of the times: And (laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) as Chriſt could not looke, or think upon <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> without teares, in regard of her ſins, and approaching ſorrowes; no more can this his ſervant, upon this Church and Kingdom without grief and paſſion: Entertaine him therefore I know you will (Chriſtian Readers) into your beſt thoughts for his Maſters ſake, whoſe likeneſſe he beares in his meaſure and degree, for <hi>ſic ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, ſic ille manus, ſic ora ferebat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now give me leave to lament a little, the miſeries of this Nation, for I could wiſh with <hi>Jeremy, That my head were even full of water, and mine eyes were fountaines of teares,</hi> continually to bewaile the ſtrange madneſſe and horrid impudence that is in this ſect of people now amongst us, who profeſſe themſelves to relate to Chriſt, and yet endeavour to deſtroy him: are <hi>called by his name,</hi> and yet would blot it out from being remembred; nay, they pretend to ingroſſe it to themſelves, as if they had more zeal unto him then other men, and loved him better, and yet <hi>perſecute his Prophets that are ſent unto them,</hi> killing ſome, beating others, and abuſing all; not ſuffering the moſt faithfull and able of them to doe his work: but caſting them out, <hi>as unſavoury ſalt, worldly filth, and the off-ſcouring of things:</hi> Is this the way to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance <hi>Chriſt into his Throne?</hi> or to promote
<pb facs="tcp:106771:6"/>the Kingdome of Heaven, which is compared to <hi>an houſhoulder that went forth at every hour,</hi> (not to caſt out, but) <hi>to call in work-men to his Vine-yard?</hi> Sure this speakes rather, that their intentions are to take Chriſts Throne from him, to lay his Vine-yard quite waſte, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to deſtruction. Indeed they promiſed at firſt to <hi>ſet up Lights</hi> in the moſt remote and obſure corners of the Kingdome, and to ſettle an allowance for them; but (alas!) they have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh'd moſt of thoſe few, which were before in ſuch places, (whereof this learned Author was one) and where <hi>Light ſhined</hi> moſt plentifully, they have introduced <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and to perpetuate that unto Poſterity, they have ſeized (as a prey) upon theſe Revenues which Ancient piety had conſecrated and ſet apart to maintaine <hi>Lamps in Gods Sanctuary</hi> to the worlds end: O woe unto us for the ſame; and a treble woe to them; how many of thoſe lamps have they put out? How many Church doores have they ſhut up? How many Congregations have they blinded or poyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, affording them no Preachers at all, or only ſuch as have skill and will to lead unto perdition? O the vaſt difference between the Spirit of him they pretend unto and theirs! <hi>When he ſaw the multitude, he was moved with compaſſion towards them, becauſe they fainted, and were as ſheep ſcattered without a ſheapheard: The
<pb facs="tcp:106771:7"/>harveſt</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>is great, but the labourers are few, pray therefore the Lord of the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt to ſend forth Laboures into his Harveſt:</hi> but theſe on the contrary ſeeing the multitude are hardened againſt them, (as appeareth) for they uſe all meanes to cauſe them to <hi>faint, they ſmite the Shepheards, that the ſheep might be ſcattered, and devoured;</hi> they think the <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt too great,</hi> and the work-men too many, and therefore their endeavours are to leſſen the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. For as concerning the rabble of <hi>illiterate men,</hi> which they have let looſe into Gods field, they merit not the name of <hi>Labourers</hi> in this ſenſe, for they work not for God at all, they gather only for themſelves, and ſcatter for the <hi>Envious man,</hi> who <hi>ſowed tares among the good corne,</hi> they have neither Ability, nor yet honeſty to till Chriſts Garden; but inſtead of dreſſing they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the ſame. So that tis evidently clear, that the Spirit of thoſe who have admitted theſe, and excluded the true work men, is not only againſt them they have caſt out, but alſo againſt the Vine-yard it ſelfe (whoſe pale, or hedge of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they have pluckt up;) or rather againſt the very Lord thereof: for is not every thing that is intituled His, in the ſame condition with his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, under the like obloquy and contempt? his <hi>Houſes,</hi> his <hi>Word,</hi> his <hi>Sacraments,</hi> his <hi>Worſhip,</hi> his <hi>Religion,</hi> his <hi>Annointed,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:106771:7"/>what ever elſe hath his <hi>Mark</hi> or <hi>Name</hi> upon it? yes alas, tis too too manifeſt to every eye: How do his <hi>Houſes</hi> lie waſte, and quite pulled down in diverſe places? in how foul a dreſſe, in what a prophane manner is that <hi>Cathedrall Church</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> (the glory of that City and of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) expoſed daily to publik view? How would our <hi>Grandees</hi> rage and ſtorme, if their owne <hi>Stables,</hi> where their Horſes ſtand, ſhould lie neglected in ſo unhandſome and ſlovenly a faſhion, as that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Temple of God</hi> doth at this preſent?</p>
            <p>How are <hi>his Scriptures</hi> alſo abuſed, miſ-inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted and miſ-applied daily, yea, and made fully as the Papiſts do affirme, like <hi>a noſe of wax,</hi> for all turnes, and for all occaſions? How are <hi>his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> contemned too, and denied to thoſe that hunger for them? yea, how are all <hi>his pure Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances</hi> caſheired and baniſhed? inſtead of wholeſome Doctrine and humble Prayers, how are they for whom Chriſt dyed, put off with vile blaſphemies, and vaine bablings? How is <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> vilified? <hi>Reading</hi> &amp; <hi>Book-learning</hi> cryed out upon, as <hi>hindring</hi> the operation of the Spirit, by which the teachers of theſe times ſpeak? But were that the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> which ſpeaks or work in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it would be rather furthered by ſuch meanes; <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> is commanded <hi>to give himſelf to Study,</hi> that he might be a fitted Inſtrument for that <hi>holy Spirit:</hi> this our Author could not have writ as
<pb facs="tcp:106771:8"/>he hath here done, but by the help of <hi>Reading</hi> and <hi>Book-learning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is that publique and moſt honourable form of <hi>Gods ſervice</hi> ſcorned, yea, ſuppreſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among us, without any reaſon at all alledged? nay, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves can charge it with no crime in the <hi>Preface</hi> to their <hi>Directory,</hi> (which is thruſt forth in the roome of it) for it ſeemes tis their purpoſe, to bring us of this Nation to the practice of <hi>blind obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> (which is no other then rank Popery;) and therefore we muſt ſubmit, not only our <hi>wills,</hi> but our <hi>judgements</hi> alſo, to this their groundleſſe and leſſe then humane innovation: their pleaſure is to prefer an Hemlock before a Roſe, and we muſt ſay tis ſweeter.</p>
            <p>How do they dote on <hi>Jeroboams</hi> way, as the moſt perfect method and plat-form of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? as he ſuppreſſed the <hi>Ancient manner</hi> of Gods Worſhip, neglected the <hi>place</hi> thereof, <hi>(1 ſt the people thereby ſhould have turned againe unto their King;)</hi> baniſh'd the <hi>Prieſts of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>admitted the loweſt of the people (that were not the ſons of</hi> Levi) <hi>into their places; yea, whoſoever would, him he conſecrated to be a Prieſt:</hi> even ſo have theſe done in all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars: and though the Text ſaith, <hi>this thing became ſin to the houſe of</hi> Jeroboam <hi>to cut it from off the Earth,</hi> yet is it made choice of by theſe men, for their speciall pattern in theſe times.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:8"/>
            <p>Nay, more then this, how are the very <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> of <hi>Gods holy Religion</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelf here ſetled, ſlighted and caſt aſide by them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wholly inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for our faith to build upon? How have many of thoſe men, who were bound in speciall to defend the ſame, (in regard of their office and calling, their frequent Oaths and Proteſtation, to that purpoſe) been the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> to alter the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the waged <hi>Balaams</hi> to blaſt and diſeſteeme them? And how have they hereby confirmed the ſlanders of our <hi>Romiſh</hi> adverſaries againſt us? who have often ſaid, that we had <hi>no Church,</hi> no <hi>Eſtabliſhed Doctrine,</hi> no <hi>foundation</hi> for our Profeſſion: How are theſe hereby raiſed in their hopes to ſee a reſtoration of their <hi>Babell</hi> in the downfall of our <hi>Jeruſalme?</hi> O that thoſe who call themſelves <hi>the Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> &amp; by their groſſe <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from their firſt faith and love, have been the chief meanes of working all theſe miſchiefes, would but read over, and lay to heart ſeriouſly thoſe paſſages, which they ſhall find to this purpoſe, in a late Book intituled, <hi>Englands complaint for the ſin of Rebellion,</hi> written by that conſtant Brother, and faithfull Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, M. <hi>Lionell Gatford,</hi> whom moſt of them well know to be a man of moſt approved integrity.</p>
            <p>But here's not all yet, not the <hi>Articles of our Religion</hi> only, but the <hi>protector of them,</hi> the <hi>Annointed of the Lord</hi> himſelf, is in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:106771:9"/>caſt aſide: How hath he been contemn'd of late? nay, how hath the Majeſty and <hi>Authority of God</hi> been vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>d in him, together with thoſe <hi>Scriptures</hi> which command our <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience?</hi> How hath His <hi>ſacred Perſon</hi> been railed upon, ſlandred and reviled? How hath He been perſecuted, hunted, &amp; tormented for His Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake? How hath he been robbed &amp; deprived of all his Revenues, his Comforts, and his Freedom, for His love and affections to the Church of God; becauſe He was the <hi>Head</hi> &amp; chief <hi>Member</hi> of it? there was too much of <hi>Truth,</hi> as there was of <hi>bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs</hi> in that speech, which ſince His Majeſty was in bondage, I heard uttered from the Pulpit by a Fryer in <hi>France:</hi> who railing againſt the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> of that Kingdome, for denying the <hi>Pope</hi> to be Head of the Church, <hi>who</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>would they have the head thereof? the King perhaps, even like their Brethren in</hi> England, <hi>who firſt made their King the Head of their Church, and now they make Him their Slave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay more yet, with the <hi>Kings Perſon and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority;</hi> His <hi>graces</hi> alſo are the object of their ſcorne and hate, His magnanimity, His patience, His care to keep His conſcience undefiled; yea the maine ſtudy and work of theſe pretenders to conſcience, theſe bawlers for Liberty of Conſcience, hath been for a long time <hi>vaſtare conſcientiam Regis,</hi> to violate the Conſcience of their Soveraign, and to breake the peace thereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:9"/>
            <p>And what dogged ſpightfulneſſe have they diſcover'd of late, againſt the <hi>pitifulneſſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> that is in Him? How faine would they be torturing and murdering of Him for His tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart towards the miſeries of His people? its well knowne to all the world, and to themſelves too, who began theſe wicked Wars, and at whoſe doore the guilt of bloodlies: yet becauſe the good King ſeeing them wholy of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> stampe, abhorring to practice the leſſon that Chriſt taught, of denying themſelves, and confeſſing their ſin; and yet being deſirous to purchaſe His peoples peace, is content (for their ſecurity of His pardon, &amp; that He will not bring them to a triall by Law, for their paſt demerits, but remit them, wholly to the hand of God) to connive even at their throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>their</hi> dirt in His face; what vile <hi>Doctrines</hi> and curſed <hi>Uſes,</hi> do their <hi>Pamphleteers,</hi> and their <hi>Pulpiteers,</hi> raiſe from thence, and preſſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people? why, that <hi>God hath now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved the great doubt, hath heard his peoples prayers, in charging the guilt of blood upon the Kings ſoule, and brought Him to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that He hath been the cauſe of all which hath been ſhed: and therefore it belongs to the people now to ſee unto it, that Juſtice be done upon Him, and upon His friends for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was ever ſuch horrid wickedneſſe heard of, ſuch tranſcendent villany in mortall creatures?
<pb facs="tcp:106771:10"/>would not the Devil himſelfe bluſh to appear in their ſhapes? may we not looke for ſome ſtrange judgement like that of the earths opening to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them up? had <hi>Davids</hi> people when he (to have them ſpared) had cryed out, <hi>tis I that have ſinned,</hi> ſpake of calling him to account for the loſſe of <hi>70000</hi> men, they had ſhewne leſſe impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence then theſe have done; Nay the <hi>malitious Jews</hi> though they crucified Chriſt becauſe he was a King, yet were not ſo ſuper-ſuperlatively vile as to conſult his death becauſe he was content in their ſtead, and for their ſafety, to be accounted as a ſinner. Aſſuredly therfore theſe men have out-gone all before them: for aske now of the daies that are paſt ſince the time that God created man upon the earth, aske from the one ſide of heaven unto the other, whether there hath ever been ſuch bloody ſpunges as theſe ſhew themſelves to be, ſuch mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of nature amongst men: O the baſeneſſe, the impiety, the wormewood, and the gall of their ſpirits! if ever the Title of <hi>Rex diabolorum</hi> was rightly applyable to the King of this land, 'tis ſince the viperine birth of theſe miſcreants. And that ſuch only as themſelves are, might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued (if poſſible) in the Nation, there is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall courſe taken, that knowledge and good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners might not abound in thoſe that come after; for the <hi>Univerſities</hi> are metamorphiſed and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged too, as well as the <hi>Church</hi> of learned and good
<pb facs="tcp:106771:10"/>men; <hi>Thiſtles are there ſet inſtead of Wheat, and Cockle inſtead of Barly.</hi> Yea all <hi>Orders</hi> and degrees amongst men (if ſome may have their will) muſt be aboliſhed preſently, and <hi>confuſion</hi> planted in all places, (as 'tis already in a great meaſure:) <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes, Nobles</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> muſt be but as the <hi>meane</hi> people; which God indeed may juſtly permit in reſpect of ſome, for thoſe contempts and miſeries which even they have help'd to bring upon his Church: ſure <hi>theſe things are a lamentation,</hi> and <hi>ought to be for a lamentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Never was there ſo fooliſh and ſo mad a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under the Sun as we have proved our ſelves, to the deriſion of all about us, the ruine and decay of our Ancient glory, our outward Happineſſe, and of our ſoules for ever. O therefore I ſay againe <hi>that mine head were full of water,</hi> and <hi>that mine eyes were fountaines of teares to bewaile theſe things.</hi> O that the people of this Land (eſpecially they that are got Higheſt) would but conſider what they have done, and yet at laſt, before all is loſt, ſet ſome period to their owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. O that thoſe men of wealth and place who advanced at firſt their whole might, to lay levell this <hi>famous Church,</hi> to take from it all Honours, orders, and degrees, would but conſider and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve well, how before that ſinfull worke of theirs is quite finiſhed; the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> it ſelf,
<pb facs="tcp:106771:11"/>(wherein their own intereſt chiefly lies) is follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apace in the ſame tract, and like ere long to lie as <hi>levell,</hi> and as low as the <hi>Church</hi> it ſelf. Firſt <hi>no Biſhop,</hi> then <hi>no King,</hi> then <hi>no Lords,</hi> then <hi>no Gentlemen,</hi> then <hi>no people,</hi> the <hi>name of England will be no more in remembrance,</hi> unleſſe as a by-word, and a ſcorn among all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>O that the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> who contrary to their many <hi>Oathes of Allegeance, Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Canonicall obedience,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> have concurred, and aſſiſted to ſuppreſſe, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>their King,</hi> to Alter and Change the <hi>Forme of Doctrine and diſcipline in this Church,</hi> would but conſider coolely and ſoberly at length of their own Doctrines and actions, and how they will be able to anſwer them before Chriſt the Judge: that they would but remember the little comfort and joy, which <hi>Balaam</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> had in that <hi>wages of iniquity,</hi> which they got to themſelves, by being the inſtruments of miſchief to other men.</p>
            <p>And I wiſh that the <hi>inferiour Clergy</hi> alſo, who by their ill tongues have helped to defame, and caſt out their fellow Miniſters, that deſired to live in peace by them; would but conſider the ſmall content which they thereby have purchaſed to themſelves: for do they reigne alone now, like Kings in their Countries, as they expected? do
<pb facs="tcp:106771:11"/>their people ſubmit quietly unto them? have they no Sectaries in their pariſhes, to torture and torment them, to with-hold their Tithes, and to preach againſt them; to ſeduce their people from them, to clamor and raile upon them, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were wont to do, upon their brethren? do not thoſe very ſpirits which themſelves bred and raiſed at firſt againſt others, flee furiouſly now in their owne faces, and make them even weary of their own lives and habitations? I wiſh they would aske their own experience and conſciences of the truth of theſe things.</p>
            <p>And for the people, I wiſh that they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with themſelves, whether they have been ſo well at caſe, ſo well moneyed, ſo well taught, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have ſo free a command in their own houſes, over their own goods, as when the Church enjoyed her rights, and Gods true Miniſters whom they have <hi>mocked, abuſed,</hi> and <hi>caſt out</hi> from among them, did preach his truth unto them.</p>
            <p>But why do I wiſh for theſe thoughts in theſe men; not conſidering with my ſelf the madneſs, blindneſs, hardneſs, and perverſneſs of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, who are ingaged in paths of death and Hell; and cannot lay to heart their own danger, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery till they are ſwallowed up by it? though we mourn in ſecret never ſo truly for their ſins, yet will not they be moved by any thing, we ſay, or
<pb facs="tcp:106771:12"/>wiſh for them; have they ever yet <hi>beleeved our report,</hi> or regarded Gods word, which we have ſpoken, ſince they entred this way? nay have they not ſaid to us <hi>their ſeers, See not,</hi> to us their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Propheſie not right things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea but however, we muſt not neglect our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which God hath injoyned us to perform unto them, and for them, though they be as <hi>bryers</hi> and <hi>thornes</hi> to us; though they have put us from our <hi>Livings,</hi> they cannot diſcharge us of our <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> we must ſpeak, we have authority from God to ſpeak, and to <hi>cry aloud</hi> too againſt them, while they be in their wicked wayes, <hi>whether they will hear, or whether they will forbear,</hi> that they may at length know and remember, there have been ſome true Prophets amongst them; let them kill us for it if they will, our blood ſhall preach and cry againſt them (louder then ever we did) when we are gone.</p>
            <p>And I beſeech all my Sequeſtred Brethren that are forbidden to diſpenſe Gods truth in Churches, (to thoſe flocks and people which God committed to them) that they would imitate this Godly Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor which is here preſented to them: imploy their Talents this other way, diſcharge their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces unto the world, caſt their ſeed about by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; who knows but God may give a bleſſing to it? <hi>Iſrael may be gather'd</hi> by it, and brought back at laſt into thoſe good wayes from whence
<pb facs="tcp:106771:12"/>they have erred; however <hi>their labour being with the Lord,</hi> they ſhall receive a recompence from their God, they ſhall die in peace, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with a good conſcience at the great day: we muſt (as <hi>S. Jude ſaith</hi>) <hi>contend earneſtly for the faith,</hi> having received it from our fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and being intruſted, to mantain it in our generation we muſt render it intire to our poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; our ſalvation (for ought I know) lies upon it; And doubtleſſe the coldneſſe of us Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to defend the eſtabliſhed truth and order in our Church, will make the ignorant world thinke them matters of ſmall conſequent and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And let us I beſeech you (all my Sequeſtred brethren) pray heartily for them that perſecute and abuſe us, that we may in deſpight of them reſtore that <hi>luſtre to the Goſpel,</hi> which they have cancell'd; and manifeſt the ſweet <hi>ſpirit</hi> thereof to be within us: let us beleeve that we are ſet thus aſide by the permiſſion of Gods providence for this purpoſe, and uſed thus by theſe men, that we having this experience of them, might be the more moved in compaſſion towards them: our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour prayed for his perſecutors, <hi>Father forgive them,</hi> and ſo did <hi>S. Stephen</hi> for his, <hi>Lord lay not this ſin to their charge;</hi> and thoſe prayers were not in vaine, the converſion of thoſe <hi>3000 (Act. 2.)</hi> is ſaid to be the effect of the one; and of <hi>Saul</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:106771:13"/>(Acts <hi>9.</hi>) is beleeved to be the iſſue of the other: and perhaps God hath determind by our prayers and our patience to convert, and ſave theſe men: Thus if we do, moſt happy ſhall we be; <hi>To you is given not only to beleeve, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake</hi> (ſaies the Apostle to us,) we are <hi>choſen</hi> out from amongst many, for this purpoſe, to honour Chriſt and <hi>his Goſpel</hi> by our ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, which we cannot performe in a better way then this; but if we expreſs it ſo, we ſhall do his will, and the <hi>ſpirit of his Glory ſhall reſt upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Readers farewell: pray for this Reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor your Learned and good friend, and for him alſo who is together with him,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your true ſervant for Chriſt Jeſus ſake, EDW: SIMMONS.</signed>
               <date>Novemb. <hi>3. 1648.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:13"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull <hi>Mr. JONA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THAN WODENOTE</hi> of <hi>Shavinton</hi> in <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe I have choſen you <hi>Patron,</hi> whom I could never yet come to know in <hi>Perſon,</hi> upon my great acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, beſides neere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, both with your
<pb facs="tcp:106771:14"/>
               <hi>Grand-Father,</hi> &amp; <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it no otherwiſe from me, then as a ſure, though meane, token of my readineſs, in all Chriſtian offices to ſerve both you, and yours, for their ſakes; and continual thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full remembrance of the <hi>Family,</hi> from whence, under God, my truely learned, and Religious <hi>Father</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived
<pb facs="tcp:106771:14"/>his firſt being. In which reſpects I humbly preſent it to you.</p>
            <p>The Lord ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the hearts, and hands of all thoſe that favour the good of <hi>Jſrael:</hi> more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſettle and inlarge his bleſsings upon you, and your poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; that you may all do worthily in <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tah,</hi> and be famous in <hi>Bethlehem:</hi> that you
<pb facs="tcp:106771:15"/>may be on earth, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments</hi> of his glory, to the good of his Church: ſo ſhall you be <hi>veſſels</hi> of glory in the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. The which is his daily prayer who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours ever in the Lord to be commanded</hi> THEOPH: WODENOTE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:15"/>
            <lg>
               <l>PErhaps, ſome Reader may account prophane,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deſcants</hi> from <hi>Records</hi> (as are here) humane.</l>
               <l>But yet all wiſe men know, how Humane ſtory,</l>
               <l>Vs'd by Divines, tend much unto Gods glory.</l>
               <l>And holy wiſdome ſweetly does extract,</l>
               <l>A bleſſed uſe of each true famed fact.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As Rich men uſe, in hoſpitality,</l>
               <l>He firſt invites thee to this century.</l>
               <l>Somewhat the better, that prepare he might,</l>
               <l>And ſatiate thy purer appetite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe courſe of ſtudy I ſo fully know,</l>
               <l>That for this Humane <hi>Century</hi> he can ſhew</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Sacred Story Chiliad</hi>-obſervation,</l>
               <l>To gratifie at full all expectation:</l>
               <l>And if unbias'd hearts theſe entertai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</l>
               <l>Hermes next time a Star will ſhine againe,</l>
               <l>And out of holy Writ communicate</l>
               <l>His rich Select's, in his Sequeſtred ſtate</l>
               <l>And though an Olive doe begin the feaſt,</l>
               <l>A Pearle, at laſt, ſhall helpe all to digeſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>P. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:16"/>
            <lg>
               <l>YOu that <hi>wed eHiſtories,</hi> and from them draw out</l>
               <l>Only the <hi>Vulgar</hi> and the common <hi>Rout</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Obſervations,</hi> mend your Pens by this;</l>
               <l>Write by this Copy you can't write amiſſe.</l>
               <l>Each Author here ſpeakes his owne mind; and we</l>
               <l>Receive their writings now for <hi>Prophecy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For our ſad Times they ſo exactly hit,</l>
               <l>As if they firſt had ſeen them, and then writ.</l>
               <l>If th' <hi>Records Pagan</hi> were, theſe <hi>Deſcants</hi> ſhall</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bptize</hi> them all; make them <hi>Canonicall.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>P. M.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:16"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106771:17"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106771:17"/>
            <head>NEW DESCANTS <hi>UPON</hi> OLD RECORDS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Adrian,</hi> when he lay a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Many Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have deſtroyed the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</hi> (a) Their contrary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts,<note place="margin">Xiphilinus <hi>in</hi> Adriano,</note> and different directions, he meant, had haſtened his death, and cut him off before his time.</p>
               <p>There are ſo many <hi>Cenſurers,</hi> and <hi>Correctors,</hi> of our, not <hi>ſick,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106771:18"/>but <hi>ſound Religion,</hi> approved by the ſacred Scriptures, and atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the blood of many faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Martyrs: There are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Reformers</hi> and <hi>Rectifiers,</hi> of all ages, ſexes, and degrees, of all profeſſions, and trades, that take upon them to order our Church, according to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall crooked imaginations; that they have reduced all things in it to a <hi>Chaos,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion: and defaced and ſpoiled one of the moſt compleat Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, if not the principall, both for doctrine and diſcipline, now extant, in the Chriſtian world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF Timotheus had not been, we had not had ſuch muſique; but if Phrynes, Timotheus his Teacher had not been, we had not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106771:18"/>had Timotheus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Meta. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> If, as he <hi>Muſick,</hi> we conſider theſe times of <hi>Mourning,</hi> we may as truly, but with deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſay, If there had not been <hi>diſcontented people</hi> abroad, we had not heard of ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and tumults, ſuffered ſuch plunderings and oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſeene ſo many wounds, and murthers; but if there had not been ſuch and ſuch <hi>Schiſmaticall Prieſts,</hi> like violent winds, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and troubling the brains of the people, and inciting them to Rebellion, we had not had ſuch <hi>diſcontented</hi> people: The <hi>people</hi> would have been <hi>peaceable,</hi> and <hi>tractable,</hi> as heretofore, had not ſome <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> been as bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and brands of Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; had not ſeditious <hi>Oratours</hi> been as <hi>Drummers</hi> in a Campe, and as <hi>Trumpetters</hi> ſounding to a battell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106771:19"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANtiſthenes</hi> the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, being asked, What a <hi>Feaſt</hi> was? Anſwered, That <hi>it was an occaſion of much ſurfeiting, and many other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders.</hi> If you make a queſtion now what our <hi>Spirituall Feaſts,</hi> the beſt liked, and moſt applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Sermons</hi> are? They are <hi>ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> and <hi>juglings</hi> for a wrong Cauſe; they are <hi>traducings</hi> of the KING, and <hi>ſlanderings</hi> of the <hi>Foot-ſteps of Gods Anointed:</hi> They are the <hi>countenancers,</hi> and <hi>promoters</hi> of <hi>Civill Warre,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the doctrine of the Scriptures, and dictate of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Conſcience: They are <hi>Alarums</hi> to ſtir up Sedition, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, Atheiſme; They are <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives</hi> againſt all Learning and Loyaltie; They are caſters
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106771:19"/>out of one Devill by another, aboliſhers of <hi>Idolatry</hi> by <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:</hi> They are <hi>the gall of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe,</hi> and <hi>the bond of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>THe Lord <hi>Elleſmor,</hi> the Lord <hi>Chancellour</hi> of this Realme, a great lover of mercy, whoſe memoriall is ſtill bleſſed, was heard to profeſſe, as I have read, that if he had beene a Preacher, this ſhould have been his Text, <hi>A righteous man regardeth the life of his beaſt.</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Prov. 12.10.</note> The Propheticall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries of the late fearfull, unnaturall War, how far were they from this diſpoſition? how far from thoughts and bowels of mercies? how far from a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to preach mercies? when it was a common courſe with them, by <hi>Vipcrine gloſſes</hi> to eate
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106771:20"/>out the bowels of a mercifull Text; when nothing was more uſuall amongſt them, then with ſtony hearts and brazen faces to alledge the words of the Scripture againſt the meaning, then to wrong, and wring the Scripture, till it bled, but they would miſ-conſtrue, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apply it one way or other, to ſtir and incite men to the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood: <hi>Arme, arme, Fight, fight, Bloud, bloud, Kill theſe Cavaliers, theſe Popiſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans,</hi> were ſtill with them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions from their Texts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CAmbyſes</hi> demanding of his Counſellors, <hi>Whether he might not marry his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter by the Law of the Land?</hi> They anſwered, <hi>They found no Law, that allowed a brother to marry
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106771:20"/>his ſiſter; but one that permitted the King of the Perſians to doe as he liſt</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus.</note>. Our proud, peeviſh <hi>Browniſts,</hi> impatient of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> a rebellious and obſtinate people, having necks as an <hi>iron ſinew,</hi> and brows of <hi>braſſe,</hi> cannot in all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures find any ſound or ſeeming proofe, for this their foule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion: Neither can their falſe Prophets, their chiefe Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, find out any ſuch places for them; but therefore they uſe, in a wrong ſenſe, ſo to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large and amplifie the great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of our <hi>Chriſtian liberty,</hi> (the which indeed is a freedome from all helliſh, ſlaviſh feare, but not from a holy, and ſonne-like feare; a freedome from the <hi>curſe,</hi> but not from the <hi>obedience</hi> of the Law) that they have now made many ſimple people, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſeene in heavenly matters,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106771:21"/>beleeve, that the reines are pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from Chriſtians necks, and they left to their owne diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; that there is a liberty pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for Chriſtians to doe what every man liketh, and to live under no obedience to <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall</hi> or <hi>Civill</hi> Governors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>WHen <hi>Mahomet</hi> was now about to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh his abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſuperſtition, wherein he had mingled the lawes and doctrines of <hi>Heathens,</hi> of <hi>Jewes,</hi> of <hi>falſe Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> with the illuſions and inventions of his own braine; he gave it forth for a maine principle, how <hi>God at the firſt to Man-kind ſent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; after him Jeſus Chriſt, who were indued with the power to work miracles; but men gave
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106771:21"/>ſmall heed to them: Therefore he determined to ſend Mahomet, a Warriour, without Miracles: that whom Miracles had not moved, Weapons might compell.</hi> They may derive their authority per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by a long deſcent from <hi>Mahomets</hi> pretended Charter, but I am ſure they can find no ſyllable of allowance, in the great, aſſured, ſacred Charter of Gods Word, who ſeeke to ſet up any Religion by the Sword: The Lord uſeth to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Church by the <hi>mouthes</hi> of Miniſters, not by the <hi>ſwords</hi> of Souldiers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>I Read of one <hi>Procuſtes,</hi> a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious theeviſh <hi>Inkeeper,</hi> who, when any <hi>Travailers</hi> came to lodge at his houſe, would make his gueſts ſtature
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106771:22"/>equall with his bed; either by ſtretching them out to the length of it, if they were too ſhort; or by cutting off ſome part of them, if they were too long: He would not fit his bed to his gueſts, but his gueſts to his bed. Nothing more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſhall we find amongſt <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> then either with <hi>ſalſe ſenſes,</hi> to ſtretch and inlarge, or with <hi>loud lyes</hi> to mince and mangle the Sacred Scriptures, that ſo they may frame them to their likings, and make them ſerve their owne turnes, at all eſſaies: They will either ſuppreſſe the words, or elſe not expreſſe the ſenſe; they will either blot out, or elſe ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh the Scriptutes, rather then they will aboliſh, or any whit alter their owne fantaſies. Of their own opinions, or writings they will not abide the very
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106771:22"/>leaſt amendment; but of the holy Word of Almighty God they care not what havock they make.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ACtius,</hi> an auncient Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedian performing his part on the Stage, was ever ſure of Commendations; but pleading at the bar, never obtained a cauſe; and being asked what ſhould be the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? his Anſwer was, <hi>That on the Stage, he made every mans Leſſon, and no man ſpake, but what he firſt contrived; he preſcribed to every one his decorum and cue as himſelf conceived beſt; but</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in the pleading place I cannot bear it ſo away, Mine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary quickly maketh me an anſwer, replyeth, oppoſeth, and ſifteth matters ſo, that I cannot maintaine a bad cauſe as I would,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106771:23"/>but it will be controlled:</hi> Our new <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> while they buz into ſuch mens eares, as are willing to hear no other teachers, while they talke, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction, amongſt their diſciples and favourers; whoſe hands and hearts they have fitted with their owne fond deviſes; they are all men of ripe and rare Gifts: Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latives, <hi>ſans peeres,</hi> whoſe meanings are <hi>Miracles,</hi> whoſe words are <hi>Oracles,</hi> whoſe lips alone are preſumed to preſerve knowledge; they may not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dip their followers, but draw them further to ſuch points, as drown men in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and deſtruction: And yet all this while all their lies are regiſtred and recorded for truth, and themſelves accounted and <hi>Canonized</hi> for <hi>Saints:</hi> But when the pride of their tongues,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106771:23"/>and the bottome of their skils come to be tryed before law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Judges, when they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto ſtrict rules of diſpute; when they are fairly hunted by an Orthodox Divine, a man of <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Parts;</hi> who can eaſily ferret them out of all their <hi>hides</hi> and <hi>holds,</hi> and either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently intangle them, or <hi>courſe</hi> them and <hi>diſcourſe</hi> them out of breath, with a full cry of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture proofes: there is not more leanneſſe, or leſſe ſoundneſſe of underſtanding lightly to be found amongſt a whole Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of men: How fitly may it now be ſaid to him that was the greateſt of note before? <hi>Alas ſilly mouſe, that appeareth after the mountaines travell!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:106771:24"/>
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>IT is <hi>harder to finde them out, then to Conquer them:</hi> could <hi>Ceſar ſay of the Scythians, they ſo hide themſelves in ſeverall caves, and in holds, and in rocks, and in towers, and in pits, even whereſoever they can be out of ſight:</hi> The chiefeſt and learnedſt <hi>Sectaries</hi> of theſe times, are ſo cloſe in their conceipts, and are ſo loath to be known what thoughts they maintain; unleſſe it be amongſt their followers (in their hearts they ever follow the faſhion of the <hi>Swallow,</hi> that delights <hi>to fly againſt the winde,</hi> but in their ſpeeches they play the <hi>Lap-wings, who flyeth aloof from their neſts, to withdraw the paſſengers thence.</hi>) Nay ſuch faire complements doe they put upon their falſe <hi>intents,</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106771:24"/>with ſo good pretences do they cloak their bad <hi>deſires,</hi> that it is much more difficult to finde out their carnall imaginations, and ſtrong holds, (the ſnares of the Devil, by which <hi>they are led Captive by him at his will</hi>) then by Gods Word to caſt them down.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>WE may read in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodotus,</hi> how the King his Fathers danger made <hi>Atys, Croeſus</hi> his dumb ſon, to ſpeake; He never ſpake before, and yet when the Souldier advanced to cut his Fathers throat, he opened his own throat, and ſaid, <hi>O man kill not my Father!</hi> What loyall Subject, what true Son of the Church can chuſe but ſhew the people now of this Land, their tranſgreſſions; when ſuch baſe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106771:25"/>and barbarous, and bloody-minded affronts, are moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefully, and unaturally put upon our gratious Soveraign, the lawfull and loving <hi>Nurſing Father</hi> of our Country! when our ſpirituall Fathers, the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhops,</hi> and paſtours of our Church, <hi>Watchmen</hi> of our ſafety, <hi>Shepheards</hi> of our ſoules, <hi>Phyſitians</hi> of our conſciences, the ſacred inſtruments, and ſilver conduit pipes to conveigh grace unto us; by whom we have been baptized, and begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the faith; are wronged in their good names, Goods and Bodies; and which is above all, when the name of the Father of us all, Lord of Heaven &amp; Earth is reproached and blaſphemed, without puniſhment or check, as if we were more incredulous then the Devils in Hell, <hi>who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and tremble.</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Iames 2.19.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106771:25"/>
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SCipio</hi> could ſay of his Souldiers in <hi>Sicily, that there was not one of them, but would, at his Commandment, caſt himſelf down from the top of a Tower:</hi> The very light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had taught them, that obedience was due to their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, though it could not direct them how far it was to be extended; and therefore they would rather afford him <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver-meaſure,</hi> then defraud him: There is no ſuch Allegeance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us, but only in things that are lawfull and laudable; and for both ſubſtance and circumſtance, we are referred to the moſt indifferent Judge the <hi>holy Scriptures,</hi> the divine <hi>Beame,</hi> and the moſt exact <hi>Ballance,</hi> by the which all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106771:26"/>in Religion ought to be determined, and may be clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: And yet, how loth and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing are we Chriſtians to give unto our lawful Soveraign, that certaine right and due, the which by Gods Word ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently belongeth unto him, in reſpect of his place?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArcus Attilius Regulus</hi> a Roman, who had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Conquered the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> was at length taken captive by them; as the <hi>Romans</hi> had taken ſome of the <hi>Carthaginians.</hi> The <hi>Carthagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> deſirous to redeeme their Country-men, and upon that condition, content to enfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chize thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had taken from the <hi>Romans,</hi> toke only an oath of this <hi>Marcus Attillius,</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106771:26"/>to returne if he did not ſpeed, (ſo ſacred, and ſure a bond was an Oath held amongſt the very Heathen) and ſo ventured to ſend him to <hi>Rome,</hi> to treat with their Adverſaries about it. He alſo for his part made ſo great conſcience of an Oath, that he preferred his oath before his life; For, when he was at <hi>Rome,</hi> where he might have ſtayed if he would, and knew, if he did goe back, he ſhould undergoe torments, and a moſt miſerable death; yet he choſe rather to expoſe himſelfe to the hands of his enemies, then to break his <hi>Covenant,</hi> and perjure himſelfe. Oh how ſhall theſe Heathen riſe up in judgement againſt us, who have the Word of God expreſly to bind us to the reverence and obſervance of an Oath! and yet many of us make no regard thereof: Have we never taken
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106771:27"/>the <hi>Oath of Supremacie?</hi> Have we never taken the <hi>Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance?</hi> Have we never been Officers? I am ſure ſome of us have: How then can our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Oathes</hi> ſtand with our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Actions?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THaerida</hi> whetting his ſword, and asked by one that beheld him, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were yet ſharp enough?</hi> Anſwered, <hi>That it was ſharper then Calamnie</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricum, <hi>659.</hi>
                  </note> From thence implying, that <hi>Calumnie</hi> ſinketh deep, and pierceth farre, and is marvellous cutting; and if a ſword be ſharper then that, it needs no more whetting. What a debaucht and deſperate Age then doe we now live in, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we not onely make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or ſcruple, to wound
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106771:27"/>ſome of our neighbours with ſwords, and <hi>ſwords</hi> ſharper then <hi>Calumnie;</hi> but moſt unworthily preſume to ſtrike at thoſe, to whom God hath ſubjected us; whom, of all others, in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, we are moſt juſtly bound to <hi>love, honour,</hi> and <hi>defend,</hi> and for whom we ought to lay downe our owne lives, if need ſhould require, both with ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>ſwords,</hi> and ſharpeſt <hi>Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>XEnophanes</hi> having the name of <hi>Daſtard</hi> caſt in his teeth, at a Banquet, for that he refuſed to play at Dice: <hi>I am, I confeſſe, a Daſtard,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and fearfull in all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt cauſes.</hi> Men are now ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Delinquents, Malignants, Rebels,</hi> if they will not in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered choler, renounce their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106771:28"/>ſubjection, break their oathes, and beare Armes, or in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner make oppoſition againſt their lawfull <hi>Soveraign:</hi> For me, let my name ſtand any where, in the moſt diſgracefull characters, though in a Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, for ſuch a <hi>Delinquent, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant, Rebell.</hi> I allow not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling, but I ſhould not grudge to be reviled for being Loyall. As with an undaunted reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Job</hi> ſaid in another caſe, ſo let me ſay in this; <hi>though mine Adverſary ſhould write a book againſt me,</hi> not only <hi>ſay</hi> what evill he pleaſe, but <hi>write</hi> againſt me, and that even an whole <hi>Book</hi> of accuſations; would I be put out of heart, or diſcouraged by it; <hi>would I not take it upon my ſhoulders, and binde it as a crown unto me</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">Iob 6.31.35.36.</note>?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106771:28"/>
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Hortenſius</hi> that ſpruce Orator im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderately prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Eloquence; wherefore</hi> (ſaid one) <hi>would he lift her up into Heaven, but that himſelf might go up with her</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">Cicero in Hortenſ.</note>? wherefore do many now adays ſo earneſtly ſtrive to ſet up their <hi>Sect</hi> above others, but that they are cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in their <hi>Sect</hi> above others; but that they may be lifted up with their <hi>Sect,</hi> and ride upon the Cherubims? but becauſe it is for their exaltation and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, that ſo they may come to be chief amongſt their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; but becauſe they may triumph upon the vantage ground of their place and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: yea, <hi>lord</hi> it over the <hi>heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</hi> and tread down their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106771:29"/>neighbours at their pleaſure?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DIogenes,</hi> that counterfeit <hi>Cynick,</hi> as it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to ſome, for all his cunning ſhewes, and crafty conveiances, pretending great humility; trampled and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed over <hi>Platoes</hi> pride, with greater pride; he laboured to diſcredit <hi>Plato</hi> to dignifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: And what do they, many of them, who now are ſo earneſt againſt <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and by calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious accuſations conſpired their diſgrace; who would faine down with <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and enjoy their Lands and Livings for their ſuppoſed arrogancy, when ten <hi>Biſhops</hi> are not arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant enough to make one now leading <hi>Presbyterian?</hi> They cry out upon the pride of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106771:29"/>
                  <hi>Biſhops</hi> for ruling according to the <hi>knowne and approved Lawes,</hi> that ſo they themſelves may be ſubject to no Law, that ſo they forſooth may come in time to rule as they pleaſe, by their own arbitrary lawleſſe injunctions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <p>ONe beholding <hi>Cardinall Wolſey</hi> when he was in the height of his pompe and pride, when, in a Letter of his ſent to the <hi>Pope,</hi> he was ſo out of his Politicks, and parts, as to put himſelfe before his <hi>King, I and my King;</hi> Not <hi>My King and I,</hi> but <hi>I and my King;</hi> could not but break out into theſe words, <hi>I pity this proud Cardinall, that neither knoweth others, nor himſelfe.</hi> What true <hi>thankfull Miniſter</hi> can now with patience endure to ſee ſo many
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106771:30"/>
                  <hi>proud Presbyters</hi> ſo ſaucily to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult and triumph over their <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> by whom they have been admitted into their ſacred fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and not expreſſe himſelf with tears, and ſay, <hi>I am very ſorrowfull for the inſolencie of theſe men, who have no remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance left, by whoſe hands they have received their Orders, and (which is more ſtrange) have no right or cleare thoughts what they are themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LYcurgus</hi> being importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to eſtabliſh a <hi>Popular Eſtate</hi> amongſt the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians,</hi> that ſo the leaſt, and meaneſt, and moſt unfit to rule, might beare like ſway with the greateſt, and wiſeſt; fitly anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, That <hi>he who moſt deſired it, ſhould begin it firſt at home in his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106771:30"/>owne houſe;</hi> preſuming that in a private family, <hi>Parity</hi> would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be long liked. There are now that ſo earneſtly long for <hi>Equality</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> that they will no longer <hi>diſpute</hi> for it, but meane to <hi>fight</hi> for it; And ſince they cannot bring it in with their <hi>tongues,</hi> they will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take help of their <hi>hands.</hi> I would all ſo minded would learne ſome <hi>wit</hi> from <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> in their <hi>anger;</hi> and firſt weigh in judgement, by the poiſe of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in the ballance of indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie, hanging upon the beame and rule of right, the inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of pulling downe all Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and eſtabliſhing communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of rule in an <hi>Army,</hi> and then conſider, whether the like equall Maſterdome may be juſtly put upon the <hi>Church,</hi> which is an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my with banners</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">Cant. 6.4.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:106771:31"/>
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <p>WHen a young man, with whom <hi>Plato</hi> found fault for playing at Dice, ſaid, <hi>Doe you find fault with me for ſo ſmall a matter? The matter is ſmall,</hi> (quoth <hi>Plato</hi>) <hi>but the cuſtome of it is no ſmall matter</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen. Laert. de vit Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophor. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>. Agood remembrance for all thoſe who have any <hi>Youth</hi> to bring up, to be very carefull to keep them from evill practices, leſt they grow paſt ſhame in ſinning; for if <hi>Cuſtome</hi> once prevaile, and get the place, it will diſcover no ſmall wicked power, it will take away all ſenſe and feeling of ſinne. But it is worth a noting alſo for another reſpect: There is great exception taken, much complaint made, and even crue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> revenge executed, becauſe ſome
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106771:31"/>Miniſters heretofore have been ſilenced, and put from their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings for <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> (the which indeed are urged, not for <hi>Ornament,</hi> much leſſe <hi>Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> of Gods ſervice, but for <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and <hi>Politie</hi> onely, and as a meane to teſtifie <hi>Subjection</hi> to the lawfull power of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</hi>) What? ſay ſome, (who little think how they have done much worſe themſelves, <hi>plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, tormented, murthered</hi>) Is it not moſt unrighteous to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict puniſhment for ſuch ſmall matters? <hi>Is it not cruell to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive men and their families of their livelyhood, for rejecting matters of circumſtance, and moaths in compariſon?</hi> The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are <hi>ſmall,</hi> I grant, but the contempt of <hi>Authority</hi> is not ſmall. But O, a great neceſſity lyeth upon <hi>Authority,</hi> to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it ſelfe from contempt.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106771:32"/>The contempt of <hi>Authority,</hi> though in the ſmalleſt matter, deſerveth no ſmall puniſhment. Wherefore were <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> condemned? Not for the <hi>fruit,</hi> but for the <hi>forbidden.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COluthus,</hi> being himſelfe but a <hi>Presbyter</hi> in one of the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> took upon him to give holy Orders: but was that his ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing approved by the <hi>Church?</hi> No: But he himſelfe was cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured for great preſumption, and they taken for meere <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> whom he had Ordained. The truth whereof is ſufficiently teſtified by two <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Learned Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church, Athanaſius</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius.</hi> From whence then, I marvell, came their warrant, who being
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106771:32"/>no more but Prieſts, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny farther <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> authority, make bold to <hi>impoſe hands,</hi> to <hi>bleſſe,</hi> and <hi>ordaine</hi> other Prieſts? Can they confirme and juſtifie this, either by the Scriptures, or practice of the Church? Was not the opinion of the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> otherwiſe? But O! what Chriſtian can chooſe but bluſh, and grieve, and groane, when they who are in no holy Orders themſelves, neither <hi>Prieſts,</hi> nor <hi>Deacons,</hi> dare order and appoint <hi>Prieſts for the people?</hi> O what a company of <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> have we now abroad, in theſe unruly times, put into office, and ſet on work but by the next great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe <hi>Schiſmatick?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:106771:33"/>
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <p>GReat was the enmity of <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> to the <hi>Romans;</hi> yet nevertheleſſe did he give this praiſe unto <hi>Fabritius,</hi> That <hi>a man might as ſoone turne the Sunne out of his courſe, as turne him from the truth and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie:</hi> He would not be ſo baſe as not to doe his mortall enemy right: He would not defraud a <hi>Roman</hi> of his deſerved commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. But O! ſelfe-love is growne now a-dayes ſo diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and envious, that if an enemy have never ſo commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable gifts, be he learned, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, humble, and in part, what not, that is vertuous, yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not afford him one good word. No, though he need encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Nay, let a mans righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, proceeding from a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106771:33"/>lively faith indeed, and contrite ſoule, <hi>exceed the righteouſneſſe of Fabritius;</hi> yet if he be but diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in affection, or diſtant in judgement from us, our lips ſhall <hi>ſleight</hi> him, if others <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend</hi> him; and <hi>malice</hi> him, if others <hi>maintaine</hi> him: Nay though they doe it, not to flatter <hi>him,</hi> but to magnifie <hi>God;</hi> Not for the increaſe of <hi>Mans pride,</hi> but for the advancement of <hi>Gods glory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <head>XXII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARiſtotle</hi> having gotten great learning from <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> by whom he was taught no leſſe then ten yeares, afterwards became a great ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my unto him, and by all meanes ſought his diſcredit. A courſe cleane contrary to all <hi>Morall</hi> rules, and even common <hi>humane</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:106771:34"/>civility: the which unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cauſed <hi>Plato</hi> to call him <hi>Mule</hi>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">Aelian de var. hiſt.</note>. The property of which beaſts is, when they have well filled themſelves with their mothers milke, to beat their dams with their heeles for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence. Well may our <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities,</hi> the <hi>Nurſeries</hi> of <hi>Gods Vineyard,</hi> the <hi>Seminaries</hi> of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Learning,</hi> and <hi>Fountaines</hi> of <hi>holy Religion,</hi> yea the eyes, the light, the temper, the ſalt, the ſeaſoning of the whole Land, take it very unkindly, that ſome of them, whom they have not onely taught, but maintained with all neceſſaries, ſome tenne yeares, ſome more, ſhould now be found their greateſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers: This may be an <hi>Ariſtoteli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> an <hi>Heatheniſh,</hi> but ſurely no <hi>Chriſtian</hi> requitall. Such unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy diſciples, diſſemblers, may be <hi>Men</hi> in countenance, but in condition <hi>Mules.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:106771:34"/>
               <head>XXIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SOcrates</hi> at a banquet fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at oddes with one of his familiars; and openly rebuking him: <hi>Plato</hi> could not hold, but ſaid unto him, <hi>How much better bad this been ſpoken privately? And had not you then done better to have told me ſo privately?</hi> quoth <hi>Socrates. Plato</hi> could ſee <hi>Socrates</hi> his fault of unſeaſonable reprehenſion, but his owne he could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve. Look but amongſt your <hi>holy Brethren,</hi> your <hi>rank Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> your <hi>devout D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſemblers</hi> now a-dayes, and they are not halfe ſo forward in examining themſelves, as in finding <hi>pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilloes</hi> in others: and they are are not halfe ſo curious in their owne, as they are captious and cruell over other mens lives.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106771:35"/>They can readily accuſe others of <hi>blackneſſe</hi> and ſpirituall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities, ſaying, <hi>They are wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, He is naught, They are An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian;</hi> but when doth any one of them, though he hath been in <hi>open Rebellion,</hi> ſmite himſelfe on the thigh, ſaying, <hi>Oh what have I done?</hi> They can gaze at the <hi>mote</hi> in their <hi>brothers eye,</hi> but care not for <hi>putting out the beame in their owne ſight:</hi> They cannot beare with a few infirmities of their <hi>brethren,</hi> no not of their <hi>Fathers;</hi> but their owne foule enormities they can eaſily conceale and continue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <head>XXIV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PElaretus</hi> a <hi>Lacedemonian,</hi> though a man highly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, was not choſen to be one of the 300. which was a degree of honour at <hi>Sparta;</hi> and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106771:35"/>yet he was ſo far from complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or grudging, or grieving thereat, that, when others mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled at his contentment, and inquired of his reaſon, he told them, That <hi>he rejoyced at the happineſſe of that Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, that it had three hundred men more worthy to governe then himſelfe</hi>
                  <note n="(m)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Plut.</hi> in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popeth.</note> How many are there in theſe times of cleare knowledge, wherein it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently knowne, that true godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe teacheth every man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment with that orbe and place wherein he is ſet, with that portion which God hath given him, (who, as ſore eyes are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at clearneſſe of light, ſo envy at the brightneſſe of other mens vertues, and proſperity: who fret themſelves becauſe of other mens wealth, or honour, and are envious againſt other mens advancement:) How many
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106771:36"/>rage and ſtorme like <hi>Aeolus,</hi> that not three hundred, nor three, but ſome one worthier perſon is preferred before them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <head>XXV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANtoninus Caracalla</hi> the Emperour, had murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his brother <hi>Geta,</hi> but was deſirous, if it were poſſible, to preſerve his own credit: A Commandment therefore was given by him to <hi>Papinian,</hi> an excellent Lawyer, to defend at leaſt, if not extoll, that his fact, before the <hi>Senate</hi> and <hi>People:</hi> But what ſaid <hi>Papinian?</hi> A murder is not ſo eaſie to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, as committed<note n="(n)" place="margin">Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianus in Caracal.</note>. By the meanes of ſome coverous, ambitious, pettiſh, and newfang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Miniſters, a ſpirituall murder hath been of late executed upon the legally confirmed forme of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106771:36"/>our <hi>Divine Service;</hi> the which hath been burned, or torne in pieces, or otherwiſe maſſacred, or made away, without any exception of thoſe ſacred parts of it, for the which they might well have forborne all the reſt: If the occaſioners of this mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (for all their rare ſuppoſed wiſdome) were themſelves, and not others for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, appointed to juſtifie theſe their own projects, not by force of <hi>Armes,</hi> but <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments:</hi> I make no doubt but they will apparently be found, though not ſo unwilling to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it, as heatheniſh <hi>Papinian,</hi> (for what dare they not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take?) yet more unable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it: <hi>Strange imaginations ſpring out of every dunghill, but ſolid and ſubſtantiall reaſons grow but in few grounds.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:106771:37"/>
               <head>XXVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LYcurgus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi>) <hi>was not ſo well adviſed, when ſeeing the Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians drink too much,</hi> and fall to drunkenneſſe, and ſo to further Sin, <hi>he commanded to cut down their Vines,</hi> and would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any to grow in that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth: <hi>It had been better</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to have digged wels near to the Vines, &amp; ſo have allai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and aſſwaged the ſtrength and licoriſhneſſe of wine with water:</hi> If our <hi>Fonts,</hi> if our <hi>Communion-Tables, Pulpits, Seates, Temples,</hi> have been abuſed in time of <hi>Popery,</hi> with a multitude of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Ceremonies, and needleſſe inventions, what? ſhall we therefore uſe them no more? Rather let us uſe them no more ſo. What? ſhall we
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106771:37"/>therefore give them over? that were ſtrange frowardneſſe and folly. Rather let us uſe them better. And even herein have we the example of our bleſſed Lord and Saviour, who did not condemne <hi>Moſes chaire</hi> for the life of a <hi>Phariſee;</hi> but prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched where they had preached, though they were notorious hypocrites, though he denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſo many <hi>woes</hi> againſt them, as againſt none more; yea, though the Temple in his time were become <hi>a den of theeves,</hi> yet then and there ſent he up devout and holy Prayers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <head>XXVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PLiny</hi> the younger, a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nym,</hi> writing unto <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> an heathen Emperour, of the converſation and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the Chriſtians of that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106771:38"/>time; confeſſeth <hi>them free from all faults, and offences, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Prince and people:</hi> except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, that <hi>before break of day, they uſually met and prayed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſang praiſes unto God.</hi> An excellent example in the general for all Chriſtians to the worlds end, to keep themſelves unſpotted from the world, and to keep their devotion at all times ſharp and ready. But O! if there were a <hi>Certificate</hi> now to be made, our Chriſtian people could not be charged with any ſuch fault; for not onely pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the <hi>week day</hi> with one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in the <hi>Temple,</hi> but even <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Sabbath</hi> is grown quite out of requeſt. <hi>Preaching,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſhew, or ſhadow of it, hath thruſt <hi>Praying</hi> quite out of doores. O <hi>Supplications,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are you fled? O <hi>Prayers,</hi> whither are you gone? O <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsions,</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:106771:38"/>and <hi>giving of thanks,</hi> what is become of you? O come againe you <hi>Supplications</hi> and <hi>Prayers,</hi> O returne you <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsions</hi> and <hi>giving of thanks:</hi> Oh that all ſuch may be uſually made againe, <hi>for all men, for Kings, and for all that are in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that we may lead a quiet and a peaceable life, in all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and honeſtie</hi>
                  <note n="(o)" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1, 2.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <head>XXVIII.</head>
               <p>I Reade, how the Chriſtians living under <hi>Preſter John,</hi> the great King of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> who profeſſeth the faith of Chriſt, though not ſo purely as it were to be wiſhed, are bound under great penalties, whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they have received the holy Sacrament, <hi>not ſo much as once to ſpit, untill the going downe of the Sun</hi>
                  <note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat. Dreſ.</note>. Fearing, no doubt,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106771:39"/>leſt they ſhould any way ſeeme to ſleight thoſe holy myſteries, wherein the unſpeakable benefit of life everlaſting, purchaſed for them by the death and paſſion of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is graciouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented unto them. There is no Nation under the Sunne, better inſtructed in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Sacraments, or any other points conducing to Salvation, then our Engliſh people are: And yet what ſmall difference are we foulely falne of late to make, betweene the Bread and Wine at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and at other common times? O are we afraid to ſpit preſently after the receiving of them? I mean, Are we afraid of giving any apparence of want of reſpect? Nay, what rude and ungodly carriages and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces proceed from many of us, both before and after wee
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106771:39"/>have beene partakers of the <hi>Lords Table?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <head>XXIX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>POlycarpus</hi> that ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Apoſtle Saint <hi>John</hi>'s Scholar, as he was led to puniſhment, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by the <hi>Proconſul</hi> to ſave his life, by the denying of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> made this anſwer, <hi>Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and ſix years have I ſerved him, and he hath never hurt me; how can I now ſorſake him, that hath hitherto preſerved me?</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">Euſeb. Eccl. Hiſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> Though not fourſcore and ſix yeares, yet many yeares, may many ſay, they have religiouſly obſerved the memory of <hi>Chriſts Nativity, Circumciſion, Paſsion, victorious Reſurrection, glorious Aſcenſion into heaven, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſending of the holy Ghoſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Diſciples;</hi> neither have
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106771:40"/>they received any evill, any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe from him all this while; O unthankful creatures, then, unworthy to live, move, or have their being, if any thing ſhould make them now, to leave off ſerving him at ſuch times, and fall a ſerving themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <head>XXX.</head>
               <p>THe humanity of <hi>Theſeus</hi> was much talked of, and wondred at, in that he vouchſafed with his own hands, to waſh the dead carkaſſes of his Souldiers ſlain at <hi>Thebes.</hi> What ſhall we ſay, or think, of the goodneſſe of our grand Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, CHRIST, Lord of Lords, who was <hi>wounded for our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsions,</hi> and <hi>broken for our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities,</hi> and <hi>with whoſe ſtripes we are healed?</hi>
                  <note n="(r)" place="margin">Eſay 53.5.</note> who for our ſake did <hi>ſweat drops of blood,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106771:40"/>trickling downe to the ground?</hi>
                  <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Luke 22.44.</note> who diſdained not to waſh away our ſins with his owne moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood? ſhall we not talk of him? ſhall we not wonder at him? ſhall we not willingly take up all occaſions to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber him? ſhall we grudge him any day that ever was celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in remembrance of any of his unmatchable benefits?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <head>XXXI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AUgerius Busbequius,</hi> ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Ambaſſadour to the great <hi>Turke,</hi> aſſureth us, that in their Synagogues they uſe ſo great reverence, that if they doe but with one finger ſcratch their heads, whilſt they are worſhipping, they think all their Devotion is loſt: yea they uſe to ſay, <hi>Would we not be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of all our reſpects, our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106771:41"/>our looks, our words, if we were to ſpeak with one of the Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaes? How much more then when we ſpeak to God?</hi>
                  <note n="(t)" place="margin">Legat. Turcicae Epiſt. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> How much worſe then are they then Turks, who come into their publick aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, where God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be more eſpecially pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, without any ſuch ſpirits of lowlineſſe and dread? with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſuch meditations or thoughts of awe to obey him, or feare to diſpleaſe him? and there ſpeak to God as unreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and raſhly, as if they were amongſt their compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Should they come with the like diſreſpect and unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly ſpeech but to an earthly Judge, <hi>Take away that ſaucie fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> ſaith the Judge, <hi>Commit him.</hi> O remember that <hi>God ſtandeth in the congregation of Princes, he is a Judge amongst Gods</hi>
                  <note n="(u)" place="margin">Pſal. 82.1.</note>: O conſider that even
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106771:41"/>Kings and Princes are to <hi>praiſe God,</hi> and all the <hi>Judges of the world</hi>
                  <note n="(w)" place="margin">Pſal. 148.11.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <head>XXXII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THeodoſius</hi> the Emperour being by perſwaſion moved to keep from the Church, till he had humbled his ſoule by true repentance, for the great murther committed by his meanes in <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> (for I cannot think that he was <hi>excommunicate,</hi> (whatſoever the Canoniſts ſay contrary) neither ſtandeth Excommunication of Princes upon any good ground, ſeeing they have no ſuperiour Judges upon earth: but <hi>How wilt thou,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> (according to his duty unto him, ſeeking to ſave the Princes ſoule with the hazard of his own life) <hi>receive the Lords Body with a bloody hand</hi>
                  <note n="(x)" place="margin">Theod. hiſt. l. 5. c. 18.</note>? was never
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106771:42"/>quiet in heart till he was freed from that impediment; ceaſed not in brackiſh teares to bewaile his wretched eſtate, and day by day with great earneſtneſſe to crave reſtitution, till he was at laſt againe received into the Church, to <hi>praiſe the Lord in the great congregation, and amongst much people.</hi> How farre from <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his humble ſpirit, and hearty love to the Church, are they now a-dayes, who have wilfully divided and rent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from our Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned our Sacraments, and condemned our Religion as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian, in the meane while betaking themſelves to private <hi>meetings</hi> and ſecret <hi>Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:106771:42"/>
               <head>XXXIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PYthagoras</hi> boundall thoſe, whom he received into his Schoole, to five yeares ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that they might not fly before they were fledge; that as ſoone as ever they crept from the ſhell, they might not aſpire to the houſe top; that their tongues might not run before their wits; that they might hear ſufficiently before they ſpake boldly: and ſo ſtrong was his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo much did his word prevaile with them, that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and conſtantly they obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his commandment. Many Tutors now a-dayes, though wiſer &amp; better then <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> yet, ſeeing their young ones too forward to make wing, cannot poſſibly beat them back into the neſt; yet cannot keep their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106771:43"/>Pupils within the limits of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners five yeares; no, nor foure yeares, till they have taken ſome Degree in Schoole, but they muſt needs in all haſte take upon them the ſacred profeſſion of preaching Gods Word; and not onely ſome thin, obſcure, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Country Pariſhes, but <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the <hi>chiefe Cities,</hi> but the greateſt congregations, and the moſt knowing people muſt take notice of their ripe and rare intelligence, in their owne, though raw in other mens opinions. Being drunken with pride, they delight to be ſeen in the moſt publick aſſemblies, as there are ſome that muſt needs ſhew themſelves in the market, or Faire, being drunken with Wine, or ſome meaner liquor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:106771:43"/>
               <head>XXXIV.</head>
               <p>THere were three Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours ſent from <hi>Rome,</hi> to <hi>Bythinia,</hi> to appeaſe the diſcords, and ſalve up the differences betweene <hi>Nicome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> and <hi>Pruſias;</hi> whereof one was troubled with an aking in his head, another with the gout in his toes, and the third with a fainting in his heart. Of this Ambaſſage what ſaid <hi>Cato? The people of Rome ſend an Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, that hath neither head, nor foot, nor heart.</hi> Were <hi>Cato Major</hi> now alive againe, to ſee our new counterfeit Legats, without any ſacred authority, without any competent ability, taking upon them ſacred functions; how worthily might he ſay of them, that they have neither <hi>heads</hi> of true learning, nor <hi>feet</hi> of right obedience, nor <hi>hearts</hi> of godly
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106771:44"/>ſincerity: Fitter for <hi>Innovation,</hi> then <hi>Adminiſtration;</hi> fitter to make differences, then to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile them; and to ſcatter the ſheep of Chriſt, then to gather them together: fitter to raiſe falſe reports, and to put their hands with the wicked to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous witneſſes, then to be righteous reformers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <head>XXXV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALexander</hi> ſeeing one of his Souldiers going to ſharpen his dart, when all other were going to fight, caſheer'd him, and caſt him out of the Army, ſaying, <hi>He was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of a place in an Army, who was then to provide Armes, when he was to uſe them.</hi> How much more is he unworthy to be a Leader in the Spirituall Army, to aſcend into <hi>Moſes
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106771:44"/>chaire,</hi> who is then to provide, when he is to put on, who is then to prepare when he is to preach? how can ſuch a one chuſe but diſguiſe the holy word of God, and prophane it one way or other? He that ſpeaketh ſodainly ſhall never ſpeake pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably, but preſumeth too far upon his owne gifts, and too much undervalueth the good of Gods people, and the buſineſſe he hath in hand. Our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ation ſhould be, as it were, <hi>ſeaſoned with ſalt, that it may miniſter grace unto the hearers;</hi> How much more when the Law of God is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly ſought for at our mouths, and to be uttered by us againſt noted and cunning Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and Hereticks; when we are openly to wreſtle, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>fleſh and blood</hi> onely, but <hi>againſt principalities, againſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106771:45"/>powers, againſt the Rulers of the darkeneſſe of this world, againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſe in high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Eph. 6.12.</note>?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <head>XXXVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AVenzoar</hi> that greatly learned, and experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Phyſitian affirmed, <hi>that he never gave purgation, but his heart did ſhake many daies before;</hi> though no doubt, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable; as long to commune with his owne heart, and with the chiefeſt Maſters he could meet withall in his profeſſion, that the cure might the better proſper under his hands, &amp; that ſucceſſe might anſwer expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: How audacious then and inſenſible, and diſſolute in their undertakings are they, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Phyſitians of ſoules, never
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106771:45"/>deliberate with themſelves what hurt bad phyſick may doe, or take any ſerious thoughts how their counſell may be moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall; who never weigh their preſcripts by the proportion of faith<note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 12 6.</note>, never ſuite their words to the wholſome words of the Lord Jeſus<note n="a" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.3.</note>, but irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, and unworthily, rudely, and raſhly adminiſter all their doctrines, inſtructions, corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, conſolations, without either dread of bad haps to fall out, or deſire of good ſucceſſe to follow, without either art or paines in the reading and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, or awfulneſſe, and heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in recollecting and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:106771:46"/>
               <head>XXXVII.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> having plucked off the feathers of a <hi>nightingale,</hi> that not long before had given a delicate and raviſhing ſound, and ſeen but a little leane carion left (b); <hi>thou art a voice,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Plutarch</hi> in Apoph. Lacon.</note> ſaith he, <hi>nought elſe.</hi> Your new faſhioned Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſo full of edification, as ſome conceive, ſeeme, in the eares of ſuch admirers, rare and excellent muſick, ſo far over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaching others notes, as the <hi>nightingale</hi> in melody paſſeth al the reſt of the birds of the wood: but pluck off the feathers from the diſcourſes, the newes, and more, newes of the times, the ſeditious contumelies, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous invectives, the idle di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions and multitude of words; as though they knew
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106771:46"/>their hearers could underſtand nothing, except they told it them twenty times over: Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robe them of ſuch their <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumquaques,</hi> and circulations to no purpoſe; wherein they run their rounds, and yet perſwade their hearers, that they goe right forward, with great ſobriety and gravity; Diſmantle them of ſuch vaine and frivolous orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, wherewith they are au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciouſly clothed; and lay them naked to the view of true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the body of all their long ſtories, what ſhew ſoever it made before the ſimple, is but a poor ſleight carcaſſe, and hath no title or matter of ſubſtance in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:106771:47"/>
               <head>XXXVIII.</head>
               <p>IT ſeemed a marvell to <hi>Cato,</hi> that a <hi>Soothſayer</hi> could ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from laughter, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he beheld another <hi>Sooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayer.</hi> And why? but becauſe the moſt ignorant of them could not but imagine, how the moſt skilfull amongſt them did but gull the people, with the couſening tricks which they played; with their pretended divinations by the liver, and the heart, and other entrailes of beaſts, when nothing can be truly diſcerned by any ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable way. And can we thinke that our new Teachers do not laugh when they meet one another, and upon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion conſider, how no Sooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiers do more deceive their <hi>cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents,</hi> then they their <hi>hearers,</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:106771:47"/>by calling hungry gueſts unto empty tables, and illuding them with the ſhew of diſhes without meat; by feeding them with <hi>words</hi> in place of <hi>matter;</hi> and <hi>roaring</hi> &amp; <hi>railing</hi> in ſtead of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons<note n="c" place="margin">Ezech. 22.25.</note>? Can we poſſibly thinke that they do not highly applaud themſelves, when they recount their wicked profits, how they have ravened the prey, how they have devoured ſouls, how they have taken the treaſures of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious things, how they have <hi>devoured widowes houſes, and for a pretence made long prayers?</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 23.14.</note> But <hi>woe unto you that are rich, for you have received your conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; woe unto you that are full, for you ſhall hunger; woe unto you that laugh now, for you ſhall mourne and weepe; woe unto you when all men ſhall ſpeake well of you, for ſo d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d their Fathers to the falſe Prophets.</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Luke 6.24, 25, 26.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:106771:48"/>
               <head>XXXIX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EIther take from thy mind, or adde to thy might,</hi> was the well ſeaſoned coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Archidamus</hi> to his Son: And indeed what wiſe man will reach above his height, or offer to carry more then he is able? Is it not a vaine thing, not to proportion our attempts to our ſtrengths, our practiſes to our knowledges? A good worke is never ſpoiled more, then when it is handled with much animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, but little ability. Oh all ye young Divines, who, for all your breaſts ſo hot, your words ſo fierce, your geſtures ſo vehement, are too forward in undertaking controverſies with the learned and politick Jeſuites, the chiefeſt of all the popiſh <hi>Rabbies;</hi> by your want
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106771:48"/>of exerciſe and weakeneſſe of judgement in the Scriptures, animating them and their diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in their errours; firſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be cunning in your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and in the light to your profeſſion, and to all your paths, the Book of God: Either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruite your <hi>learning,</hi> or reſtraine your <hi>Zeale.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="part">
               <head>XL.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SYlla</hi> the noble Roman, who was commonly moſt free and liberall, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of <hi>Marius</hi> the younger's preferment, how unbeſeeming, and dangerous it was, ſaid, <hi>that a young man was firſt to be appointed to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are, and then to the ſterne;</hi> O how much more is this order to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly thought upon and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully kept in the government of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106771:49"/>the Church, the chiefeſt Ship that ever was built; where, as the calling is weightier, ſo the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is greater, when Paſtorall charges are committed to unfit perſons; oh then that now old and young are put to ſteere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can row; oh then that now men and boyes are ſet as notable <hi>Pilots</hi> to direct the Ships of Chriſtian congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, how to ſaile through the tempeſts and waves, and to paſs the ſands, and rocks, whereby in this ſubtile world they are ſubject to miſcarry; before they have learned themſelves to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void one rock, either of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption or deſpaire! before they are any whit experienced in their ſpirituall <hi>Card</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, the Word of God,</hi> by the which their whole voiages are to be directed, and levelled; they are deſigned to governe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106771:49"/>Ships loaden with more coſtly fraights, then the whole world and all the glory thereof is able to countervaile<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 16.26.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="part">
               <head>XLI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CIcero</hi> comming into the Province, which his brother <hi>Quintus,</hi> a very little man governed, and ſeeing his picture drawne in a very great ſtature, could not hold but merrily ſaid: <hi>Halfe my brother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hole</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Macrob. Satur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>. What large acclamations and eminent promotions, are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped now adaies, upon ſome men by their favorers, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they approve their waies, &amp; conforme themſelves to their conditions, willing to wallow in the ſame puddle with them, ready to run with them to the ſame exceſſe of riot; or though
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:106771:50"/>they do not in all humors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, yet becauſe they conſent and joyne with them, in ſome hereſies, ſchiſme, or faction: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the valuation of whoſe worth and rewards, what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion can any man find? Are ſuch men worthy to be magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, to be mounted? Are ſuch men fitteſt to be placed in the chiefeſt roomes above others; becauſe they ſtrongly ſupport a ſide, and are wily perhaps to contrive miſchiefe; howſoever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> any good medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions wonderous weake, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expert, yea ſilly for their owne ſouls, and altogether without underſtanding of the matters of God? How juſtly may their impartiall brethren ſay, when they ſee ſuch men aloofe, and applauded, that <hi>halfe ſuch prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, halfe ſuch preferments, if they be duely conſidered, are more
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:106771:50"/>then ſuch mens whole deſerts?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="part">
               <head>XLII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SImeones,</hi> beholding <hi>Arſaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> an unlearned and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy man, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (whatſoever <hi>Cyrill</hi> partially thought of him) placed in S. <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> roome, a Father ſo Learned, ſo Godly, ſo skilfull in the Scriptures, cryed out, <hi>O ſhame who is here placed? whom doth he ſucceed</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Niceph. Lib. <hi>13.</hi> c. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note>? We may juſtly ſay the like of many of the late intruders, both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Fellowſhips in Colleges, and Benefices in the Country, <hi>what are theſe? in whoſe roomes do they come?</hi> Are not falſe and flattering prophets, time-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, trencher Chaplaines, ſet up in the roomes of Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox and conſciencious Divines? Are not greene heads not growne unto any ripeneſſe of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106771:51"/>judgement, obſtreperous bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, ſaucy Sub-Jacks poſſeſſed of the preferments of the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Ancient? Are there not thruſt into the dignities of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet, pious, and loyall Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, cauterized wretches, ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks and Rebels, as if they were to be tutors and factors for hell? And yet I am not ſo ſorrowfull that theſe things ſhould be done, as that they ſhould be practiſed under a counterfeit colour of <hi>Religious Reformation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="part">
               <head>XLIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COme not to me, as if I were a neat-herd, but yeild me a reaſon of thy dealing,</hi> quoth the ſick <hi>Philoſopher</hi> to the <hi>Phyſitian;</hi> He would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to take Phyſick, though from a kind Phyſitian, upon
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106771:51"/>meere <hi>preſcription;</hi> but he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ſome farther aſſurance; and muſt have ſome ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing allegation: If thou come as a Spirituall Phyſitian to cure the ſores of any ſoul, come not to me with winning words as he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks uſe, who are wont firſt to <hi>incite,</hi> and then to <hi>inſtruct;</hi> who in ſtead of <hi>reaſons,</hi> uſe <hi>exclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> (broken reeds for any man to leane upon, that hath any care of his ſoul) who cry out <hi>luſtily,</hi> but confirme <hi>lazily;</hi> but come to me with pregnant <hi>proofes,</hi> as true Prophets obſerve, who are accuſtomed firſt to prove, and then to perſwade; I like not theſe ſelf fet aſſertion, as if all the world were bound to the breath of other mens mouths; ſhew me a proof for that point thou wouldſt have me to beleeve or follow: prove what thou preacheſt, if I ſhall
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:106771:52"/>beleeve thee; I ſhall ever im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace one <hi>full proofe</hi> before a thouſand flaunting <hi>proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> Tell not me of uſes only, and uſes upon uſes, I ſhall ever be afraid to make uſe of the roome of that houſe, where I am ſtill in doubt whether the foundation be ſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="part">
               <head>XLIV.</head>
               <p>IT was an heroicall anſwer which was given by <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth Emperour to ſuch as would have perſwaded him not to ſend back <hi>Luther,</hi> being come unto him under his ſafe conduct; that though the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances of promiſes were cleare baniſhed the face of the earth, yet they ſhould be kept by an Emperour. Going often into the Sanctuary of God, and having there clearly found ſo
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:106771:52"/>many precepts, for the reverent handling of Gods word, the which I hope, they have promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to keepe, what though Miniſters now adaies be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly perſwaded and urged to take the name of God in vaine, and to Preach <hi>extempore?</hi> what though otherwiſe they are like to looſe all eſteeme amongſt worldly men, and to be outed of all their meanes? yet is it a good reſolution for every Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher that feareth God, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and obſerve without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception: Be the impudent guize of others applauded, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and preferred; be fear and reverence baniſhed from the Church, I will never preſume to aſcend a Pulpit, without pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and publick both <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>premeditation:</hi> By me the ſacred word of God ſhall never willingly be prophaned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="part">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:106771:53"/>
               <head>XLV.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <hi>Cteſiphon,</hi> for that he vaunted that he could diſcourſe all the day of any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject that was put unto him; they thought that words ſhould not be long and empty, but ſhort and the ſubject of much matter; but like pretious jewels, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine great riches in a little roome: They conceived that ſpeech ought to be ſo precious a treaſure, as not to be uſed in vaine and waſtfully: But have the people ſuch an evill conceit now adaies, of <hi>copiam verborum,</hi> of over-flowers with words, who for a drop of <hi>wit</hi> have a floud of <hi>elocution,</hi> who truſt more to the ſlipperyneſs of their tongues, then to the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their cauſe; (or though
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:106771:53"/>they do not baniſh them,) do they miſlike to hear them? Do they not rather thinke their wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to be as fluent as their words? Do they not rather take them for the beſt preachers, that can moſt vary phraſes, and talke longeſt, and loudeſt, though nothing to the buſineſs? though much mudde of vanity muſt needs iſſue out, where the ſluce of moderation is plucked up, and paſſage given to all that can be ſpoken. And yet how could the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> come to hear what we have often heard, that <hi>for every idle word,</hi> though neither in it ſelf falſe, nor yet hurtfull, and prejudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all unto others, and therefore much more for tedious Sermons full of <hi>tautologies,</hi> (beſides un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, treacherous, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane matters) a ſtrict account <hi>there muſt aſſuredly be rendred.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="part">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:106771:54"/>
               <head>XLVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AUguſtus Caeſar</hi> on a time, as he was paſſing through <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſaw certain ſtrange women lulling <hi>Apes</hi> and <hi>whelpes</hi> in their armes; <hi>What,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>have the women of theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries no other Children?</hi> You that ſo admire and run after thoſe, as the only profound Teachers, who were never bred as Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; who underſtand not one of thoſe tongues wherein the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt</hi> wrote, (great helps to learne his meaning) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot convince hereticks, as true Miniſters ought; for the tranſlations often faile; and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alwaies expreſſe the force of words in the Originall; can you find in neither of our famous Univerſities, ſo learned and ſo holy men, as theſe your new
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:106771:54"/>
                  <hi>mountebanks,</hi> that can mount from the <hi>boate</hi> or the <hi>coach</hi> to the <hi>desk,</hi> from the <hi>ſhop-board</hi> to the <hi>Pulpit?</hi> can you meet with no ſtronger workemen then ſuch weake <hi>hinds?</hi> no better <hi>leaders,</hi> then ſuch <hi>blind guides?</hi> no skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuller <hi>Pilots,</hi> then ſuch as never ſailed one league from the ſhore?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="part">
               <head>XLVII.</head>
               <p>WHenſoever <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Great heard any plaintiff, he was wont to ſtop one eare; and being asked why he did ſo? anſwered, <hi>I keepe the other free for the defence of the accuſed; that ſo I may ſtand indifferent till the truth be throughly canvaſſed:</hi> If an <hi>heretick,</hi> or <hi>ſchiſmatick,</hi> mutineere or Rebell can get the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:106771:55"/>firſt acquaintance with ſome men; he may eaſily ſo foreſtall and fill both their ears with a falſe report, as to leave no roome for any farther informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; He may quickly lead them, or rather miſlead them, whither his perverſe humour inclineth. The firſt tale cunningly told car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without baile or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize into any crazed opinion, or carnal reſolution whatſoever, againſt their Country, Prince, yea God himſelfe. <hi>Alexander</hi> was not more reſerved, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, then they are weake and wilfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="part">
               <head>XLVIII.</head>
               <p>WE read of them who dwell about the fall of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Nilus,</hi> where it tumbleth downe from high mountaines,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106771:55"/>that they are made deafe by the greatneſs of the ſound and noiſe of the waters. The many great and ſtrange lies that in theſe deſperate times have been ſpread abroad by loud-ſounding Trumpets, all the Kingdom o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; the tumultuous noiſe that all <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and <hi>conformable Divines,</hi> are <hi>ranke Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Popiſhly affected;</hi> that their faith and ſervice is curſed and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; that a ſet forme of <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Prayer</hi> is <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> and abominable, and no more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, then the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>of ſwines fleſh</hi> was under the Law, which the Lord abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; have made many of the common people (and ſome no doubt who have a devotion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to ſerve God aright) ſo hard and dull of hearing, that they cannot now for their hearts and ſouls perceive the ſtill and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:106771:56"/>ſoft voice of the truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="part">
               <head>XLIX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WAlter Mapes</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Arch-deacon of <hi>Oxford</hi> (the next age after the Conqueſt) having written of a groſs Simoniacall bargaine made by the Pope, ſhutteth up his narration thus; <hi>Notwithſtanding let our Lady and Mother the Church of Rome, be as a ſtaffe bowed in the water, and let us not beleeve what we ſee</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">De Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Can.</note>. Let a true Proteſtant give but any the leaſt advantage of ſuſpition, let him but looke over the hedge, (be the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint never ſo falſe, the proof never ſo ſlender, the man never ſo guiltleſſe) the horſe is ſtoln, and he muſt needs be the man; There is no pleading to be made to it, there is no beleeving the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:106771:56"/>contrary: but let a <hi>brother of the faction</hi> apparently commit a moſt foule offence, let him be taken in the manner; let the caſe be clear by ſufficient wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; yet we muſt not beleeve all that we hear, or ſee, both our eares and our eyes may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; the man may be right ſtill as a ſtaffe in the water, how bowed, how crooked ſoever it appear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="part">
               <head>L.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEnelope</hi> but a heatheniſh woman, was ſollicited by many unchaſte wooers to wrong her husband <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> who had been abſent from her twenty years: yet neither by <hi>ſuiters</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, nor her owne Parents in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties, could ſhe be drawn to breake her faith which ſhe had made to her husband at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, but ſtill remained faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:106771:57"/>What Regiments, what Fleets of <hi>ſchiſmaticall</hi> and <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall wooers</hi> are now in the world, who under pretence of devotion, zeale, and good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendments <hi>compaſſe Sea and Land</hi> to make one of their profeſſion? and what a great cunning crew of them in theſe Kingdomes? every man ſtriving, what he may, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance and advantage his cauſe. Theſe <hi>wooe</hi> the ſilly and ſimple ſort of people, and with words of deceit ceaſe not to entice <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſoules,</hi> to wrong Chriſt, to breake covenant with him, and contract themſelves with <hi>new husbands</hi> (new Lords, that have new Laws which Chriſt never uſed:) but ô take heed and beware, let none of theſe wooers <hi>wooe</hi> you; or if they <hi>wooe</hi> you, let them not <hi>win</hi> you: be true to Chriſt your loving <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> your
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106771:57"/>true <hi>bridegroome,</hi> your dear <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign,</hi> your gratious <hi>Saviour;</hi> O forget not his parables, his precepts, his ſentences, his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, his prayer, his peace that he left with you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="part">
               <head>LI.</head>
               <p>IT was <hi>Annibals</hi> ſaying of <hi>Marcellus,</hi> that <hi>he had to do with him, who could never be quiet, neither Conqueror nor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Plate in vita Annib.</note>; but Conquering he would purſue his victories, and Conquered labour to recover his loſſe: but much rather may a man ſay the like of <hi>Satan,</hi> that great ramping Lion, the Arch-envier of our peace and happineſſe, who is the moſt wrathfull and the moſt watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full enemy, who is never idle but ever imployed in ſowing <hi>cockles</hi> amongſt the Lords <hi>good
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:106771:58"/>corne;</hi> who, though we ſtoutly <hi>reſiſt him,</hi> and overcome him for a time, yet will never reſt nor give over, but will be tempting againe; yea will not ceaſe to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay us againe and againe with the ſame temptations, hoping at length to win our conſents, and to give us the foile. Wherefore having often well fought againſt him, and ſubdued him, yet <hi>watch</hi> we ſtill, and <hi>pray</hi> we continually to God, that we be not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtered by him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="part">
               <head>LII.</head>
               <p>I <hi>Would never ſit upon that ſeate,</hi> ſaid <hi>Themiſtocles, from which my friends ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no more benefit from me, then ſtrangers;</hi> And indeed how often do friends ſway the ballance of Juſtice? who hath not ſeen how private reſpects cauſe too many Judges, to leave
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106771:58"/>the truth, and to hear the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood? but ô the Scriptures teach <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> a clean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary leſſon, when they put on the perſons of <hi>Judges,</hi> to put off the perſons of <hi>friends;</hi> when they ſit in the place of Juſtice, not to thinke they are now huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, or parents, or kinſmen, or neighbours, but <hi>Judges,</hi> and therefore without all by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, to diſcharge that truth, which the great God of heaven and earth hath repoſed in them, and expecteth from them, not once remembring their foes for any <hi>preſſures,</hi> and altogether forgetting their friends for any <hi>partiality.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="part">
               <head>LIII.</head>
               <p>I <hi>Socrates</hi> an <hi>Athenian</hi> Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, in his counſell to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monicus</hi> (a young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106771:59"/>man like to be called to a great place) ſaith thus unto him: <hi>Depart not from an Office more rich, but more honourable, then when thou undertookeſt it.</hi> The inſtruction given by this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then may ſhame many Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; our Officers regard not with what diſhonour, or diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, they keep or leave their places, ſo they may be rich: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fear though they tread their Wine out of other mens grapes, reape their corne out of other mens fields, ſo they may ſtore their owne houſes with proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo they may make their children great, and turne them into gallants, they take no care, make no ſcruple, though they turne their own ſouls into hell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="part">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:106771:59"/>
               <head>LIV.</head>
               <p>IT is written of <hi>Charles of Prague,</hi> that he ſupped often with a few ſentences, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments in the Schooles<note n="m" place="margin">D. Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred. in vita Juelli.</note>, his meditation was all the meat he had for that meale: But if ſome of the moſt devout Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators now a daies moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding with lip holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, were reſtrained and tied for a while to no better allowance; (the which yet were great kindneſſe to their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous ſtraitneſſe and continuall cruelty towards their priſoners) there is no doubt to be made, but you ſhould quickly hear them complaine of <hi>ſhort com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons;</hi> I make no queſtion but you ſhould ſoone hear them with no ſmall paſſion exclaime upon their perſecutors malice,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106771:60"/>covetouſneſſe, pride, ſeeking by others ruines to be Grandees, and to advance their heads a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all that is called their neighbour: you ſhould then hear at large of their owne good breeding, great worth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, (whereof they were never guilty:) you ſhould then hear the ſubjects property diſplaied and ſet forth at full, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Laws and reaſons, both humane and Divine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="part">
               <head>LV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HErod,</hi> as we find in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick hiſtorie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king full account to deſtroy Chriſt, amongſt the reſt, not only ſlew all the other chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, near the place where Chriſt was borne; but ſpared not his own child, the fruite of his own loines, fleſh of his fleſh,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:106771:60"/>and bone of his bone<note n="n" place="margin">Euſcb. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> Macrob. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turu. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note>; what bones made he to pluck up that affection to his child, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had planted in him, or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſet unnaturall murther in the place? The which being reported to <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <hi>It is better</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to be Herods ſow then his ſon:</hi> To ſuch heavy ſufferings, to ſuch hard diſtreſſes, to ſuch evident and extreame calamities have they been driven to in theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull times, who have ſpent their times, their ſpirits, their lives, their patrimonies, for the good of the Church: ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable and violent wrongs and oppreſſions have been practiſed of late upon grave, learned, and conſcientious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, the <hi>chariots and horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of our Iſrael;</hi> by <hi>the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and footmen in our Iſrael,</hi> that juſt cauſe have they to cry
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106771:61"/>out and ſay to ſuch perſecutors ſhame, (ſaving the honour due unto God) <hi>Better be the peoples plowmen then Priests.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="part">
               <head>LVI.</head>
               <p>IT was the <hi>Poets</hi> vaine and groundleſs conceit of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> that <hi>ſo long as he lived, Troy could not be deſtroyed;</hi> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming him the <hi>immovable and inexpugnable pillar of Troy:</hi> But well may it be ſaid of a faithfull man, that he is a mighty ſtay, &amp; ſtrength, a maine defender and upholder of the place where he liveth, for whoſe ſake, for whoſe preſence, and prayers, out of the Lords abundant kindneſſe to all his, even the wicked are often within the ſhadow of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, &amp; ſpared: as for one juſt <hi>Lot</hi> the <hi>Angels</hi> ſpared the City <hi>Zoar; Zoar</hi> might perhaps be as
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106771:61"/>bad as <hi>Sodom,</hi> but here was a difference, <hi>It had a righteous Lot within, Sodom had none</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 19.21.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="part">
               <head>LVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DIonyſius</hi> the younger, confeſſed that <hi>he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained many Sophiſters, not that he did admire them, but that for their ſakes he might himſelfe be admired:</hi> Though there be no great number now a daies that are further liberall to Scholars, and Miniſters, then only in outward comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; yet, I fear, a great part of them alſo part not with their kindneſſes to pleaſe God, who requireth it at their hands, whom they ought to make reckoning of above all; and to ſupport and relieve thoſe Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Religious men who need it, whom they ought to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106771:62"/>love as themſelves; but rather in a Phariſaicall humor to advance their own credits and reſpects in the world; that, how foul ſoever their projects are, they may car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them on with faire lookes; that what injurious or irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intents, what ſecret ſins, or diveliſh drifts ſoever they have, they may yet be thought to be great lovers of Learning, and Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="part">
               <head>LVIII.</head>
               <p>I <hi>See many bodies; countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and garments of Romans, but no Romans,</hi> quoth that great Captaine <hi>Marcellus</hi> unto his Souldiers: Many bodies and boroughs of bodies, many ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and devout lookes of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and attires not unbefit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Proteſtants, may there be found now abroad in the world:
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106771:62"/>Never was hypocriſie ſpun with a fairer thread, never were men more cunning in counterfeiting; but if you caſt your eyes from their <hi>lookes,</hi> to their <hi>lives,</hi> from their <hi>words</hi> to their <hi>works,</hi> by the which the moſt ſubtile ſouls may beſt be diſcerned, the copy of mens actions is more plaine to be read, then the copy of their countenances. You ſhall find that you are much miſtaken in your cenſures; for where is the life of grace, the <hi>power of godlineſſe?</hi> you ſhall perceive that they are no true and reall Proteſtants all this while; but <hi>aliens from Chriſt,</hi> void of Gods ſpirit, without faith, without hope, without love, and in brief, meere hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, like <hi>Balaam</hi> or <hi>Saul,</hi> or rather more formall, like <hi>Satan</hi> himſelf, when the <hi>witch of Endor</hi> ſuborned him in the <hi>mantle of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:106771:63"/>Samuel,</hi> and brought him into the preſence before <hi>Saul</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">1 Sam. 28.28.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="part">
               <head>LIX.</head>
               <p>THere was a ridiculous Stage-player in the City of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing <hi>O heaven, let downe his finger towards the ground;</hi> The chiefeſt man preſent beholding it, could not abide to ſtay any longer, but left the company &amp; ſaid in anger; <hi>This foole hath made a ſoleſcime, hath ſpoken,</hi> as it were, <hi>falſe Greek with his hand:</hi> There was no conformity he meant, between his tongue and his hand. O how many ſuch ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd actors are there every where to be found, pointing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, poiſing downwards; pointing at heaven, practiſing earth; who carrying the light of the Goſpel in their
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:106771:63"/>mouthes, carry alſo in their hands the filthy water of ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and covetouſneſs to quench it withall; who ſeeke in word Gods <hi>cauſe,</hi> but breake in deed Gods <hi>Commandments;</hi> whoſe words are the <hi>words of God,</hi> but their deeds are the <hi>deeds of the Divel.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="part">
               <head>LX.</head>
               <p>A Painter, being reproved for drawing the picture of S. <hi>Peter</hi> too high colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, made anſwer: That he <hi>drew him not as he was on Earth, but as he was in Heaven; where he bluſheth to behold the ſhameleſs demeanors of his ſucceſſours:</hi> I am not now to learn that <hi>Peter</hi> is ignorant of us here upon Earth, and knoweth not his ſucceſſours; neither am I yet untaught that he is not yet bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106771:64"/>in Heaven; but howſoever, if a Painter were truly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cypher any good man now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, he had need make him much more high coloured then he was wont to be; for where is there one ſuch that doth not bluſh to ſee ſo many apparent paraſites, creeping up to honors through a thouſand diſhonours, ſo many Chriſtians in profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo many Saints in ſhew, now adayes, that have <hi>Jacobs Voice,</hi> and <hi>Eſaus Hands,</hi> that can give <hi>Judas Kiſs,</hi> &amp; <hi>Joabs Curteſie,</hi> wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon by a ſecret ſtab, when he baſely killed <hi>Abner</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">2 Sam. 3.27.</note>; and againe, when as lewdly he killed <hi>Amaſa</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">2 Sam. 20.10.</note>? where is there one ſuch that doth not bluſh to behold ſo many dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-faced <hi>Januſſes,</hi> various and inconſtant pretences, change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Chamelions, apt to all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, taking the colour of what
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106771:64"/>is next them? where is there one ſuch that doth not bluſh to view ſo many like the <hi>Mariners needle</hi> without the touch, which will turn every way, and never ſtand ſtill the way it ſhould?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="part">
               <head>LXI.</head>
               <p>WHen <hi>Charles,</hi> the ninth of <hi>France,</hi> propounded to that famous Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> this three-fold choice: <hi>Either Maſs, or Death, or perpetual Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the moſt Chriſtian Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy made this worthy Anſwer. <hi>God aſsiſting me, I will never chuſe the Maſſe; the other two I referre to the Kings determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet ſo as I hope God, in whoſe hands the heart of the King is, by his gratious providence will guide &amp; diſpoſe of theſe alſo.</hi> But how few now will ſuffer any the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106771:65"/>leaſt hardſhip for Chriſt? If men may avoid death, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and riſe upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ruines; if they may eat of the fat and drink of the ſweet<note n="ſ" place="margin">Nehe. 8.10.</note>, if they may eat the good things of the Land<note n="t" place="margin">Eſay 1.19.</note>, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe what Religion you will, either Maſſe or Mahumetiſme, or what elſe ſoever; you ſhall have ſervile creatures enough, baſe fellowes of all degrees, that wil be any thing, or of any Sect, that will fit you every way, that will faſhion and put forwards themſelves for any imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the good Centurion ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver kept ſuch obedient, ready and reſolute ſervants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="part">
               <head>LXII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARiſtotle</hi> hearing a proud prauncing <hi>Thraſo</hi> ruffling in his fuſtian brags; vain
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:106771:65"/>gloriouſly talking of his own vertues, and repreſenting a great outward appearance of worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>I wiſh</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I were ſuch a one in truth, as thou think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy ſelf to be, or wouldſt ſeeme to others to be, but to be as thou art, I wiſh to mine enemies.</hi> I dare not deſire to the worſt of mine enemies that they may be as many of your new Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts are, whoſe out-ſide is of lambs wool, but their in-ſide of foxes fur; <hi>Cato</hi> without and <hi>Cataline</hi> within; who by fits and upon occaſions make a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous verball ſhew of goodneſſe, when in heart they are nothing like to what they make ſhew of: but I wiſh that my ſelf and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were, which ſome of them no doubt ſeeme to themſelves, and all of them would faine ſeeme to others, walking in all the Commandments and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106771:66"/>of the Lord without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="part">
               <head>LXIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IUlius Caeſar</hi> in his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries writeth of the <hi>French</hi> Souldiers, that in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the battell, at the firſt on-ſet, they were more then men; but at the ſecond, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the end, leſſe then women: They would talke bravely, and come on couragiouſly, but at length give off cowardly. How many hypocriticall hotſpurs in our reformed Churches ſhall a man meet, who have Gods word ſwimming in their lips, but not ſhining in their lives; who if words may be received, their pay is gallant; but if deeds be required, their money is not currant; who in profeſſing and proteſting are more then
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:106771:66"/>Proteſtants, but in preaching, and performing, and perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leſſe then Papiſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="part">
               <head>LXIV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BAtus</hi> the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Prince moved by <hi>Innocentius</hi> the fourth, to receive the Chriſtian Religion, ſent his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours to <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſearch and underſtand their belief, and manner of Religion; who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting that the Chriſtians lived wickedly, and worſhipped they knew not what Images contrary to the doctrine they profeſſed; the <hi>Tartarian</hi> received the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of <hi>Mahomet:</hi> What Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan can we now hope to win, to ſeeke to be one with us, to become a member of our Church, when he ſhall ſee our faith turned into faction, our Religion into Rebellion, our
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:106771:67"/>patience into violence, our zeale into ſelf-love, our fidelity into perjury, our Chriſtian humility into moſt cunning hypocriſie, that would ſeeme to hate hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie? when he ſhall eſpie us to have bread in one hand, and a ſtone in the other? when he ſhall hear us talke like Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and ſee us live like <hi>Turkes?</hi> when he ſhall find the words of our mouthes ſofter then butter, having war in our hearts? when he ſhall perceive our ſpeeches ſmoother then oyle, and yet they be very ſwords<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 55.22.</note>?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="part">
               <head>LXV.</head>
               <p>IT was divinely ſaid by <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, though an Heathen, when he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the <hi>Queſtor</hi> for being too bountifull in his Sacrifices; <hi>If thou deſire long to be happy, be
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:106771:67"/>not niggardly to God in matters that belong to his worſhip; which if they doe not flouriſh, all other things are ſure to decay.</hi> O in what other matters are we ſo ſparing and baſe? in reſpects of our pleaſures, of our profits, of our honours, how readily can we laſh out ſo many and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pounds, not caring what we ſpend? but when any thing ſhould come from us to a good purpoſe, to a charitable uſe, but when we ſhould do wel, willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and freely to disburſe, how faſt fingred, and cloſe handed are we? but for the better ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and maintenance of the ſervice of God, and advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his glory, not a farthing more can we afford to part with, then what we are taxed and forced unto. And yet what a gratious promiſe have they, who <hi>honour the Lord with
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:106771:68"/>their ſubſtance, and with the firſt fruits of all their increaſe? So ſhall their barnes be filled with plenty, and their preſſes ſhall burſt out with new wine</hi>
                  <note n="w" place="margin">Pro. 3.9, 10.</note>?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="part">
               <head>LXVI.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writeth that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour, when he died, had a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter care of the Church, then of his ſickneſs; his life was not dear unto him, ſo the Church might flouriſh after his death; ſo <hi>peace might be within her wals, and proſperity within her palaces.</hi> Now if men may enjoy health, and obtaine plenty for the back, and the belly, waxe rich and great, and live like Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, no matter which way Religion turneth, or what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth of that ſtate and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, no matter how the Church
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:106771:68"/>fareth either for the future or preſent; how it goeth with the Church they reſpect little, ſo themſelves and their families may go on. Nay, which is yet a worſe ſymptome, and bewray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the great power of Satan over them; what ſcruple at all do they make, to pill, and ſpoile, and rob the Church, ſo as they may enrich themſelves and their poſterities?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="part">
               <head>LXVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CAepio</hi> with his Souldiers robbed the wealthy Temple of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Narbon</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> near the Pyrene mountaine; but of thoſe that had a ſhare in any of thoſe goods, not one ever proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red<note n="x" place="margin">Guevara.</note>. It was ſo generally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that it occaſioned a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb; If any man (by what
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:106771:69"/>meanes ſoever decayed) were fallen into poverty, they would ſay of him, <hi>He hath ſome of the gold of Tholouſe.</hi> The indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all other Churches (whereof many have been plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of rich Chalices, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther utenſils in theſe ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous times) are like the gold of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> that brought ruine to them and their families; If any man thrive with them, that hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them by a wrong tenure, he hath better ſpeed then any ſuch malefactor before him. How many Sacrilegious perſons have utterly ruinated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, it is eaſie to find in many Monuments of learning; how a canker hath eaten their eſtates, as a gangrene did their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; but ſee the Chronicles, ſearch Hiſtories of ſundry Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, both ancient and moderne, and find me out but one
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:106771:69"/>Church-robber here that hath thrived paſt the third generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="part">
               <head>LXVIII.</head>
               <p>I Have read that many things have been given to our Churches with <hi>a curſe in the Churches, againſt any ſuch as ſhould ever preſume to take them away:</hi> Whether mans curſe ſhall take hold of Church-rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, is wholly in the diſpoſition of God, and a ſecret; but I am ſure he himſelf hath openly cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all thoſe, how many or great ſoever they be, that <hi>rob him in Tythes and offerings</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Mal. 3.8, 9.</note>, yea curſed them with a curſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubling the words, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great cauſe, but emphatical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſignifie that they ſhall be curſed with a ſtrange curſe, a ſignall curſe, ſuch a curſe as <hi>he
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:106771:70"/>that heareth his ears ſhall tingle, and his knees ſmite one the other;</hi> and many learned, religious, and wiſe men thinke, that this Land now mourneth, as for other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, ſo eſpecially for this great robbery; the grand, the common, the far-ſpreading, the crying ſin of this Kingdom. As all <hi>Iſrael</hi> was plagued till <hi>Achan</hi> was puniſhed; ſo they fear God will not leave to ſcourge us, till we have rooted out all of <hi>Achans</hi> generation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="part">
               <head>LXIX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PIttacus,</hi> one of the ſeaven wiſe men of <hi>Greece,</hi> being asked counſell, <hi>whether in marriage it were beſt, for every one to chooſe his equall,</hi> bad him that asked him go to children playing at fence, and they would tell him; every one to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106771:70"/>his match. If they which are ſo greedy to take away that, which hath by devout people, many years ago, been given to the Church, for the better main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Gods worſhip, were ſo wiſe, as firſt to be adviſed, whether it were lawfull; it were no unfit anſwer for them, to bid them go learn of children; who hold it both undecent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, to give a thing to one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and then take it away: and therefore much more rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is it to take from God, what hath been a long time gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto him, and accepted by him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="part">
               <head>LXX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEtrus Bleſenſis</hi> making re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Arch-deacon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaid: <hi>It was a Dragon, a ſtately name,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:106771:71"/>or title, Arch-deacon of London, not having whereof to live ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of wind;</hi> not having meanes, he meant, to maintaine a man of breeding, and parts fit for that place. Were our preſent Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy preferments exactly ſurvey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and duly conſidered, with the corrupt cuſtomes, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, the common couſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, conſpiracies and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which they are ſubject unto, I verily beleeve they would moſt of them be found more then half empty caskes, of more ſound then ſubſtance, ſo purloined and impaired at the leaſt, that they are nothing near the value, whereunto they are raiſed in the worlds opinion; and therefore had more need of reſtoring, then abſtracting phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="part">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:106771:71"/>
               <head>LXXI.</head>
               <p>MAſter <hi>Lambert</hi> who wrote the Perambula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Kent,</hi> a man of ſound judgement in his owne profeſſion, the Law, and above many others of his time, of great knowledge in Divinity; ſpeaking of a <hi>Kentiſh</hi> Benefice converted into an Impropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; thus delivereth his cenſure upon it; <hi>One amongst many of thoſe monſtrous births of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe, begotten by the man of Rome in the darke night of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition; and yet ſuffered to live in this day-light of the Goſpel, to the great hinderance of learning, the impoveriſhment of the Miniſtery, and the infamy of our Chriſtian profeſsion.</hi> Now then if our new incomparable Saints, who drcame of ſo great
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:106771:72"/>perfection in themſelves above others, hate all things that have been any way abuſed to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, in times of Popery; yea though it be a ſincere prayer, or ſacred ejaculation, firſt deviſed and uſed by ſome holy Father, or glorious Martyr; how much more ſhould they abhor all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt impropriations, whereof ſome have been, a long time heretofore, perverted to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous uſes, and all undoubtedly derive their originall from groſſely Popiſh parents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="part">
               <head>LXXII.</head>
               <p>HOw odious a creature was a traytor to that <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Nobleman, who was commanded by <hi>Charls</hi> the fifth, to lodge the Duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> at his houſe in <hi>Madrid: I will obey thee,</hi> ſaith he to the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:106771:72"/>Emperour, <hi>but ſet my houſe on fire as ſoone as the Duke is out of it: My predeceſſours never buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it to harbour traytors</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">The ſtate of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives.</note>? Was not his houſe built to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour traytors? &amp; was any good mans houſe built to entertaine ſacrilegious perſons? who make it a point of conſcience, a part of Religion, to devoure what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to Religion, that Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy men forſooth may not ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit upon what God hath thought meet to allow and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point for them. Can any that fear God wittingly make much of thoſe (unleſſe it be in extream neceſſity) who deſperately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to rob God? Now ſurely though <hi>treaſon</hi> be a great and a grievous ſin, a common over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrower and deſtroyer of hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; yet what is it in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>ſacriledge? Treaſon</hi> is a roaring ſin, but <hi>ſacriledge</hi> a
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:106771:73"/>thundering ſin; And the reaſon is rendred by S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Cont. Creſcen. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note>, <hi>becauſe it cannot be committed, but more directly then other ſins, againſt almighty God. You have robbed me</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal. cap.</hi> 3.8.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="part">
               <head>LXXIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALexander</hi> ſaid he was more bound to his Schoolemaſter <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> then to his Father <hi>Philip;</hi> for by his Father he <hi>lived,</hi> but by the other he had learned to <hi>live well:</hi> Alas a poor <hi>well,</hi> may you well ſay, when neither he nor his maſter knew the Lord: but ſurely much more doe we owe to thoſe miniſters, who have begotten us in the faith, then to thoſe parents who have begotten them in the fleſh: but ô how then beyond all cry, and above all compariſon, are we
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:106771:73"/>for ever obliged to the Father of us all, Almighty God, who <hi>worketh all things after the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of his owne will</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.11.</note>, who gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth words to the wiſe, and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue unto their words, who gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth a bleſſing to the word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, making it frultfull by the grace of his Spirit, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the heart?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="part">
               <head>LXXVI.</head>
               <p>IT was a debaucht and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſpeech that of <hi>Tiberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, When I am gone, let hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth be confounded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and mingled in their old Chaos:</hi> True charity, though it begin at home, and ſeeke firſt her own, yet ſeeketh not only her own, but looketh a broad, regardeth others, and reacheth in a provident care even to thoſe that ſhall come after us; A
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:106771:74"/>faithfull man thinketh it not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to be loving and benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to others, yea to let his fountaines (proceeding all from the fountaine of goodneſſe) be diſperſed amongſt them du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his own daies, but holdeth himſelf bound to have a further reſpect what ſhall become of them when he is dead and gone. And is there a future carefull proviſion to be made, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our ſeverall places, for private families after our death? And is there no care to be taken for the continuance of the Common-wealth and Church, that the truth of God may live when we are dead; that God may have a people to ſerve him after our departure?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="part">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:106771:74"/>
               <head>LXXV.</head>
               <p>IT is reported of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, that when he could not handſomely unty the knot of <hi>Gordius</hi> King of <hi>Phrygia,</hi> he hewed it aſunder with his ſword: The doctrine, government, and diſcipline of our Church well twiſted and made ſo exactly with the bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and teſtimonies of the Prophets and Apoſtles, yea Chriſt himſelf our bleſſed Lord, and Maſter, that the cunningeſt cenſurers, and malitious make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, of the former or of this latter age, could not find any moderate meanes to untwine them; there were ſome there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that reſolved to take <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anders</hi> violent courſe, and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them in pieces with ſwords: but herein they have far exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:106771:75"/>
                  <hi>Alexander,</hi> for he cut in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but a ſenſeleſſe knot without any hurt to <hi>Gordius;</hi> but theſe have not onely cut aſunder the knot, but have withall firſt mangled, tormented, and then deſtroyed many ſenſible, reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and faithfull ſervants of the moſt high God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="part">
               <head>LXXVI.</head>
               <p>MAd <hi>Fimbria</hi> brought a ſtrange action, even in the heathens opinion, againſt <hi>Quintus Mutius Scaevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> for not receiving the whole weapon, when he cauſed him to be wounded, into his body<note n="d" place="margin">Cicero pro Sext. Roſc.</note>: But ô how much more ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and madly have whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies and flocks been of late ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, condemned, puniſhed, for not receiving poyſon into their ſouls; for not admitting,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:106771:75"/>as lawfull, into their Creeds, hatred, variance, malice, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, riots, rebellions, errours, hereſies, the doctrines of Divels, forged in hell, and not framed in the ſhop of the Scriptures? And who are they that are thus cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bent, that are thus fierce and violent towards their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; but they who would ſeeme not only to be Chriſtians, and good men, but the chiefeſt ſervants, and deareſt children of God, the moſt holy brethren, the moſt ſanctified people, ſuch as are all for the ſincerity of the Goſpel, and pure milke of the word?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="part">
               <head>LXXVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LUcius Neratius</hi> tooke a great pleaſure, &amp; thought it no ſmall glory, to beat men: but however he cauſed his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:106771:76"/>ſervant ſtill to carry along with him a purſe of money, that when he had done he might deliver them ſuch recompence, as the Law had aſſigned in action of battery<note n="e" place="margin">Aulus Gellius.</note>. Many there are now adaies, who, though they do not ſtrike men, yet do as bad, and worſe, plunder them, oppreſſe them, undo them, and all thoſe (how harmeleſſe, how many ſoever) that belong unto them, but where is the money for recompence, that both the Law of God and man requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth? They delight as much, and more, in wronging of men, then ever <hi>Meratius</hi> did; but who with him deſireth to make ſatisfaction?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="part">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:106771:76"/>
               <head>LXXVIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THraſilaus</hi> a frantick man amongſt the <hi>Grecians,</hi> whenſoever he ſaw any Ships brought into the haven at <hi>Athens,</hi> thought them all his own, and tooke an Inventory of their goods, and boaſted of them to all he met with great alacrity<note n="f" place="margin">Alemoeus Deipnoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſt.</note>. The late plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, thoſe peremptory day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theeves, that without conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or covert tooke away ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny honeſt mens goods, and were not afraid by impudence to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and boaſt of their takings; if they had been, as <hi>Tharſilaus</hi> quite diſtraught of their ſenſes; and out of ignorance imagined all that they ſaw to be their own; with the which they might do what they liſted; they had not had ſin; that is, not ſo
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:106771:77"/>great ſin, not ſo black, and barbarous, and horrid ſin: for ſomething might have been pleaded for them, to have leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their offences; It might have been prayed for them, <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Luke 23 34.</note>: But ſurely knowing both the Laws of God, and man againſt them, and pretending that they fought for, the property of the Subject, therefore now they are left without excuſe, therefore now they have no cloake for their ſins: ô, if ever their conſciences be awakened, how can ſuch au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious preſumption but fill their hearts with the ſharper grief, and their faces with the greater ſhame?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="part">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:106771:77"/>
               <head>LXXIX.</head>
               <p>THere were that would needs perſwade <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> that <hi>he was no mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man, but an immortall God;</hi> but when, at the ſeige of a City, no ſmall wound was given him by an arrow, ſo that he ſaw the blood ſtreaming from it, <hi>where are they now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that ſaid I was a God</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Muſc. in</hi> Pſal. 82.</note>? A great fame was heretofore ſpread abroad of ſome of our new Donatiſts, that they were moſt juſt men, ſuch as feared God and eſchew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed evill; yea if not Gods in the likeneſſe of men, as the men of <hi>Lyſtra</hi> thought of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Act. 14.11.</note>, yet the moſt holy children of the moſt high God; but now ſince they have been ſo deſperately wounded by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and ſtirred up to all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:106771:78"/>cruelty, now ſince they have ſhewed themſelves ſo bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and deceiptfull men, now ſince they have ſhed the <hi>Saints blood like water round about Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 79.3.</note>, beſides their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing defiled with many other ill-favoured corruptions: where are now their followers, their admirers, their applauders, that ſo boaſted up and downe of their truth, and peace, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? where are they that thought them ſo humble, ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, ſo ſhining with all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly vertues?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="part">
               <head>LXXX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAladine</hi> a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, he that firſt of that Nation Conquered <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">l 11 86.</note>, lying at the point of death, after many glorious Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, commanded that a
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:106771:78"/>white ſheete ſhould be borne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him to his grave, upon the point of a ſpeare, with this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation: <hi>Theſe are the rich ſpoiles which Saladine carrieth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with him, of all his triumphs, and Victories; of all the realme; and riches he had, now nothing is left but this:</hi> Why ſhould we ſo much deſire other mens goods, and ſeeke to get them by hooke, or by crooke? why ſhould we devour <hi>houſes,</hi> even <hi>widowes houſes?</hi> why ſhould we encroach upon other mens fields, and ſeeke unlawfully to <hi>joyne land to land, calling the lands after our own names</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Pſa. 49.11.</note>, entailing them upon childrens children, to make (as the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers</hi> ſpeak) a perpetuity, when at laſt, if we could conquer ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much, we muſt come to the pit with <hi>Saladine,</hi> and carry
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:106771:79"/>nothing away with us but a ſhrouding mantle?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="part">
               <head>LXXXI.</head>
               <p>IT was ſound direction that <hi>Silla</hi> gave, that <hi>the common enemy ſhould firſt be put out of power, before the Citizens were put in ſuite.</hi> We ſhould firſt <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly contend for the faith, which was once delivered unto the Saints,</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Iude 3.</note> and not give place to dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable doctrine, though it ſhould coſt living and life: we ſhould firſt with all our indeavours ſeeke to ſuppreſſe all <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Hereticks, Rebels, Church-robbers, Mahumetans, Atheiſts,</hi> and other enemies of our Churh, and State; the which make a land to languiſh ſooner then forraine foes; and we fall out and fight with, or plunder
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:106771:79"/>and oppreſſe (for what cauſe we know not our ſelves) our fellow-Proteſtants, faithfull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, loyall Subjects, and harme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe neighbours; we perſecute Saints and purſue our brethren: all our fraies are againſt our friends, and not againſt our foes; we ſupplant one another, who ſhould ſupport one another. O that theſe home-bred contentions and controverſies might at length ceaſe, and be blowne away with a breath of mercy in Chriſt! ô that there might be a perpetuall holy league between all the true members of our Church, that ſo all our Armies and forces, pikes, and pens, wits, and wils might be readily combined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our common adverſaries!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="part">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:106771:80"/>
               <head>LXXXII.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> in their publick feaſts, uſed to foxe ſome of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, (a kind of ſervants not much differing from ſlaves) that by their loathſome inundations, and uncouth deformities, their rude and beaſtly behaviour, their children might the better diſcerne what a filthy vice drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe was, and from thence grow into an horrour and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of that ſin<note n="p" place="margin">Plat. in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theg.</note>. We may not, I know for any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects (though to ſtave off o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from inſurrection) either occaſion, or allow one Rebell. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thine heart, thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy neighbour, and not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſin upon him</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Levit. 19.17.</note>. But ô, if we might lawfully do it, yet in
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:106771:80"/>theſe times we need not, ſuch unruly cattell are now grown both innumerable, and intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; Their miſchiefs are gone out into all the Land; and their abominations unto all our neighbour Countries: Neither we nor our fathers have known ſuch horrid fruits of reſiſting Soveraigne power, as our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren have now ſeen; ô that they may ever retaine ſuch an eager abomination of all ſuch Atheiſticall enormities, as to hate even the leaſt thought ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereunto!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="part">
               <head>LXXXIII.</head>
               <p>I Find it related by <hi>Herodotus,</hi> how <hi>Cyrus</hi> intending to Conquer <hi>Scythia,</hi> came to a great broad River which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred his journey, whereupon he bethought himſelf of this poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:106771:81"/>to cut it, and divide it into many parts and ſluces, and ſo made it paſſable for all his Army; The like policy hath the Divel now uſed amongſt us, bringing his power of darkeneſs to invade and over-run us, and finding his paſſage ſtopped by the flowing ſtreames of love and concord, he hath put in practice to ſeperate and divide us into many parts and factions: we are become like rivelets not joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, but every man running his owne way, ſo that the Divel may now ford us, and faſhion us, and turne us as he pleaſe. <hi>My bowels, my bowels, I am pained at my very heart, my heart maketh a noiſe in me, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hold my peace, becauſe thou haſt heard ô my ſoul, the ſound of the Trumpet, the alarum of wars: Deſtruction upon deſtruction is cryed, for the whole land is ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led;
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:106771:81"/>ſuddenly are my tents ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and my curtaines in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; How long ſhall I ſee the ſtandard, and hear the ſound of the Trumpet</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Ier. 4.19, 20, 21.</note>?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="part">
               <head>LXXXIV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PAulus AEmilius</hi> having put away his wife <hi>Papinia</hi> without any cauſe, as it ſeemed to others, ſtretched forth his foot, and ſaid: <hi>You ſee a new and neat ſhooe, but where this ſhooe wringeth me, not you, but I alone know:</hi> meaning, that there were many ſecret jars hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening between the married, which others could not poſſibly perceive<note n="ſ" place="margin">Plut. in vit. P. AEmil.</note>. The moſt wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, the greateſt enemies to God and his Goſpel, may be ſo jocund and merry, and ſhew ſuch magnanimity in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that none can imagine by
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:106771:82"/>any outward circumſtance, but that they are truely cheerfull, and couragious in their hearts; and yet in the middeſt of all their meriments, and greateſt delights, they may have ſecret heart-burnings, and grievous vexations, what God and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves only know; <hi>The Lord hath ſpoken it twice, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt needs be plaine and peremptory, that there is no peace to the wicked</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Eſay 48.22.57<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21.</note>; Their lookes may be ſometimes lively, but their hearts are alwayes heavy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="part">
               <head>LXXXV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DIonyſius Heracleotes</hi> a ſoure and ſevere defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of that Stoicall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feelingneſs of paſſions, being tormented in his reines; cried out, that <hi>all things were falſe which he had till then held, and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:106771:82"/>maintained of paine and griefe:</hi> as that it might be eaſily borne and endured whatſoever it was; for now he felt the contrary, that paine pincheth and will be felt, and is able to make the ſtrongeſt ſtoope, notwithſtanding all plaiſters of phyloſophie and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane reaſons: A wounded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, many no doubt thinke, is not ſo hard to bear, as ſome talke, may eaſily be ſalved up by many outward carnall helps, Feaſting and merry company, eating and drinking, muſick and gaming, and things of like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, can eaſily ſmooth it over; but if ever they feele it indeed, they will aſſuredly confeſſe, that all ſuch medicines are nought worth againſt ſpiritual qualmes, and that the horrour of a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied conſcience is an importable burthen, no way to be aſſwaged
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:106771:83"/>but by the only mediation of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="part">
               <head>LXXXVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PHilip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon</hi> ſaid that <hi>he was bound to the Athenian Oratours which reviled him, becauſe they were to him, as fire to gold, wind to corne, file to ruſt, ſoape to linnen; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were an occaſion to make him the more vertuous; and adviſed, and enforced him, all his life long, both in his actions and words, to prove them lyars: I will therefore ſo live,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that no man ſhall beleeve them, that if I cannot bar the mouthes of the ſlanderers, yet I may ſtop the eares of the hearers</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Plutar. in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theg.</note>. There is hardly now a learned, Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe, and conſciencious Divine amongſt us, that is not traduced
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:106771:83"/>for a Papiſt, by a ſort of ſawcy, ſchiſmaticall, hungry cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, that gape for our meanes; how wiſely ſhall we profit by their malitious reproach, if thereupon we carry our ſelves, every day to the end of our lives, more virtuouſly then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, having better conſciences, that whereas they ſpeak evill of us as evill doers, they may be aſhamed that falſely accuſe our good converſation in Chriſt<note n="w" place="margin">1 Pet. 3.16.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="part">
               <head>LXXXVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CRates</hi> having loſt all by ſhipwrack, <hi>go too fortune,</hi> quoth he, <hi>I know what thou meaneſt, thou intendeſt only to call me to Phyloſophie:</hi> Thus he, being a Pagan, that knew not fortune from God. And ſhall Chriſtians no ſooner begin to fall into miſery, but be at their
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:106771:84"/>wits end? ſhall not they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the end of Gods afflicting them, that he doth it to inſtruct them, the better to know him, themſelves, and the world? to know him whom they have ſo often offended, and turne unto him by true repentance; to know their mortall and fraile nature, that weareth and waſteth away with outward croſſes; to know the mutability of the world, and the deceitfulneſſe of the world; ſhall not they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that <hi>when they are judged, they are chaſtened by the Lord, that they ſhould not be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the world</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">1 Cor. 11 32.</note>?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="part">
               <head>LXXXVIII.</head>
               <p>I Read how <hi>Phydius</hi> was apt for all practiſes, could turne his hand to any trade, could ſhew his cunning as well in any
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:106771:84"/>other mettall or matter as in braſſe: This cannot all doe, neither is it fit for all to do: <hi>Let every man abide in the ſame calling wherein he was called</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.10.</note>. <hi>Study to be quiet and to do your owne buſineſſe,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle.<note n="z" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4 11.</note> It is not fit for men to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in other mens trades, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall we likely find ſuch another <hi>Phideas:</hi> but howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a true Chriſtian, though he cannot faſhion his hand to every trade, yet ſhould learne to frame his heart to every eſtate; he ſhould know how to riſe, and how to fall, how to want, and how to abound; he ſhould be able to ſwimme in proſperity without pride, and to ſuffer in adverſity without peeviſhneſſe; humbly and thankfully imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing whatſoever favour the Lord ſendeth him, and kiſſing whatſoever croſs he laieth on his back.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="part">
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:106771:85"/>
               <head>LXXXIX.</head>
               <p>IN the <hi>Olympian</hi> combatings ſet forth and ſolemnized in the honour of Sathan, they only woare the Crowne, who overcame by doing harme to others, they which ſtruck the greateſt blow went away with the prize: but in our ſpirituall conflicts, not they which ſtrike, but theſe which bear the greateſt ſtroake, ſhall go away with the reward; they rather are Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who win the victory by ſuffering wrong of others: ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering is the way to glory. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they which ſuffer perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for righteouſneſſe ſake, for theirs is the kingdome of heaven;</hi> for as they ſuffer here with Chriſt, ſo they ſhall raigne here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after with Chriſt. <hi>Bleſſed are ye when men ſhall revile you, and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:106771:85"/>perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evill againſt you falſely for my ſake. Rejoyce, and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding glad, for great is your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in heaven: For ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted they the Prophets that were before you</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 5.10, 11, 12.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="part">
               <head>XC.</head>
               <p>WHat a bitter and cruell wrong was that offered to <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperour, when his ungratefull ſubject and ſervant <hi>Phocas</hi> ſlew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his face his Wife and five Children? And yet were not his thoughts ſo much upon the Adverſary to be vexed, as upon the righteous God to be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: <hi>And yet ſpake he not one word to the enemy; no, not in ſuch a woefull caſe</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Abbas Urſ. <hi>158.</hi>
                  </note>: but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering &amp; weighing his own ſins,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:106771:86"/>continued ſtill crying, till the ſword ſundred his head from his body, <hi>juſt art thou O Lord, and juſt are thy judgements.</hi> Why then do we (of inferiour places, ſo many degrees behind <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi>) in theſe times of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo earneſtly looke to the heavines and grievouſnes of the wrongs offered? why then do we ſo paſſionately preſſe the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe and injuſtice of the outward agents and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? why do we not rather looke up, as we ought, to him that ſitteth at the ſterne, and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all particulars? why do we not rather recount and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how many wayes we our ſelves have offended God, and our neighbours, for which we may juſtly ſuffer? why do we not rather conſider that it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not upon us without our deſerts, becauſe God is juſt, nor
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:106771:86"/>will it be without our profit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God is good?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="part">
               <head>XCI.</head>
               <p>EXceeding is the love of earthly heatheniſh mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to children; when <hi>Agrippena, Neroes</hi> mother, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with child with him, was after great conſultation ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fore-told by Aſtrologers, that her ſon ſhould be Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, but when he was advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, ſhould kill his mother; <hi>let me be ſlaine,</hi> ſaith ſhee, <hi>ſo he may raigne;</hi> and much more no doubt is the love being bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ordered by Gods word, of true Chriſtian parents; but ô how infinite is Gods love to his adopted ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? <hi>Can a woman forget her ſucking child,</hi> ſaith the Lord, by the Prophet Iſaiah<note n="c" place="margin">Iſay 49.15.</note>, <hi>that ſhe
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:106771:87"/>ſhould not have compaſsion on the ſon of her wombe?</hi> as though it were a thing even impoſſible, that any thing ſhould be able to maſter, or kill that affection, ſhe were to be reckoned as a monſter amongſt women that ſhould want it; but ſuppoſe any ſhould, for it may be, yet the Lord for all that, cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get any of his whom making him their God, he hath made his ſervants; yet will not, yet cannot the Lord forget the pooreſt ſoul in the world that truſteth in him; and therefore be not faithleſſe, whoſoever thou be, if thou be his, but faithfull, and therefore caſt all thy care, thou troubled ſoul, ever upon the Lord, for he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="part">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:106771:87"/>
               <head>XCII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT is not Kingly,</hi> quoth <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus</hi> the King to a poore man begging a ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but a dram of ſilver, <hi>It is not for Kings to give trifles, but to give royally like themſelves.</hi> How bountifull then muſt we needs think is the King of Kings, with whom no King is to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, who hath all treaſure in his owne hands, and whoſe treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry can never be drawne dry; who hath in his hands all the goods and bleſſings both of this life which is preſent, and of that which is to come! How rich is he in mercies! how abundant in kindneſſes! How large is his love, giving more things, and more plentifully, then either we doe ask or think? <hi>If any man lack wiſdome,</hi> or any other good
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:106771:88"/>gift, <hi>let him aske of God, which giveth to all men liberally,</hi> which giveth not ſparingly, though the ſmalleſt gift be more then we are worthy of, <hi>but liberally, and reproacheth no man, and it ſhall be given him.</hi> Jam. 1.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="93" type="part">
               <head>XCIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CEſar</hi> purpoſing to paſſe into <hi>Africk,</hi> though the rough ſurges of the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſeas were againſt him, chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up the Maſter of the Ship, and bade him be confident to hoyſe up ſayles, and commit himſelf to the fury of the ſtorm, becauſe he carryed him that was ſo mighty a Monarch: and yet, had he rebuked the violent winds, or the unruly waters, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much, they would never have yeelded him the leaſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. How much rather ſhould
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:106771:88"/>a Chriſtian not be diſmayed, but Magnanimous, to whom Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Be of good cheere, I have overcome the world</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Ioh. 16.33.</note>? I have already won the field, and obtained the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory for you? O how ſhould a Chriſtian be <hi>ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might,</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.10.</note> againſt all aſſaults of tyrants, all temptations of Satan, to whom God hath ſaid,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> that <hi>he will never leave him nor forſake him,</hi> neither in wealth, nor want, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in life, nor death? O how ſhould a Chriſtian be incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt all dangers, either of body or ſoul, <hi>in whom God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and he in God?</hi> 1 Joh. 4.15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="part">
               <head>XCIV.</head>
               <p>IT was not a ſlight and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial, but ſolid, though ſhort advice of the Philoſopher
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:106771:89"/>
                  <hi>Menedemus,</hi> to <hi>Antigonus</hi> the ſonne of King <hi>Demetrius,</hi> that <hi>he ſhould remember he was a Kings ſonne:</hi> thinking that a ſufficient motive to keepe him from all baſe behaviour. And how could he well conclude o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe? For doth it become Princes ſo to deſcend, as to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the conditions of Peſants? ſhould not they ſeek to demean themſelves in all their carriages according to their high places? O Chriſtian man, what art thou? Know thy calling, and conſider the bleſſed ſtate of Chriſtian profeſſion; Thou art the ſonne of God, thou haſt his Spirit, the earneſt peny, the pawn, the pledge, the inunction, the cry of his Spirit. But by what meanes? Through faith. In whom, and by whoſe merits? In Chriſt, <hi>For ye are all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God by faith in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:106771:89"/>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">Gal. 3.26.</note>. And ſhall we not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſcorne and hate ſin, ſo unfit for our eſtates, and ſo unſeemly for the children of God? And ſhall we not therefore abſtaine from immoderate mourning for worldly loſſes, too baſe and meane for our calling?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="95" type="part">
               <head>XCV.</head>
               <p>A King of <hi>France</hi> hearing the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> titles at large rehearſed, as that he was King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi> King of the <hi>Sicilies,</hi> and many other Dominions, oppoſed to every one of them ſeverally, and to all of them joyntly, but onely this, that <hi>he was King of France:</hi> he made account that <hi>France</hi> was more excellent then <hi>Spaine,</hi> and all the reſt annexed King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: A true Chriſtian in the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:106771:90"/>pooreſt eſtate, if you weigh him with the richeſt worldling, is, as <hi>France</hi> was by him concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and compared with <hi>Spaine,</hi> though not ſo great in title, yet greater in truth; though not ſo good in outward ſhew, yet bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in inward ſubſtance; <hi>Thou haſt put gladneſſe in mine heart,</hi> ſaith David, <hi>more then in the time, that their corne and wine increaſed</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſal. 4.7.</note>. As much as to ſay; thy favour, O Lord, hath brought me more true, and ſound joy, then others take, or can take in this, that their reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues and incomes do abound.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="96" type="part">
               <head>XCVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SEleucus</hi> comming back with a company of armed men to <hi>Babylon,</hi> from whence he was expelled, as he made haſte into the City, ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:106771:90"/>and wreſted his foot: His friends moved at it, heaved up the ſtone, at the which he tooke his hurt, and finding under it a ring, in which was engraven the forme of an anchor, ſuppoſing it to portend captivity; but <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leucus</hi> underſtood it otherwiſe, that the anchor, which they thought to ſignifie captivity, did certainely portend and promiſe conqueſt and ſecurity: <hi>Be cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageous my friends,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for this ground, whereon we now tread as aliens and exiles, we ſhall undoubtedly poſſeſſe as heires and owners.</hi> Wicked men if any croſſes befall them, they begin to ſinke down under the burden, their hearts faile them, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and take things in the worſt ſenſe; but the children of God being aſſured upon better grounds then <hi>Seleucus,</hi> make no other account, but are reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:106771:91"/>and confident, that neither good can happen to the evill, nor evill to the good being changed by the bleſſing of God: that all things, of what ſort ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, by one meanes or other, ſhall in the end, without perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, worke together for the beſt unto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="part">
               <head>XCVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ECebolius</hi> a Sophiſter of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> before <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> was Emperour, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaned himſelf as an earneſt Chriſtian, both for belief, and life; under <hi>Julian</hi> he became a cruell Apoſtate, and Panym and perſecutor; and after <hi>Julian</hi> was dead, he would be a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an againe: but his owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence at laſt accuſing him for his diſſembling, for altering his faith, religion and manners ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:106771:91"/>to the time; he caſt himſelf flat upon the ground, before the Church-gate, as the people ſhould paſſe, and cryed, <hi>Tread on me that am unſavoury ſalt.</hi> O how many in theſe times have been on all ſides, as the ſides ſtill prevailed! who, though they caſt not themſelves down at the Church door, as he did, for the people to tread upon, yet have need preſently to caſt themſelves down, in the inner temple of their hearts, before God, with hearty repentance and humble confeſſion, leſt if they make no account of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering his favour, and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themſelves to him, he ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly caſt them out indeed, as unſavoury ſalt; for as he hath a time of mercy, and ſuffering, ſo of caſting out and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="part">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:106771:92"/>
               <head>XCVIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALexander,</hi> having beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged any Rebellious Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, was wont to have a fire kindled before the gate, with this condition, that if they yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before the fire went out, they might be received to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; but if not, they might looke for no mercy: The like courſe doth God take with us all the ſpace of our life, as of that fire kindled, as given us to repent in; but if it end, before our repentance begin, no place for pardon. Yet there is hope, yet there is favour, yet the light appeareth, but when we are once ſtept over the threſhold of death, no man may make agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with God for us: when we are once departed this life, it is too late to make any prayers
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:106771:92"/>for us, to deale any doles, or to ſay Maſſes, or to go any Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages for us, yet it is too late then to ſay for any, <hi>God have mercy on his ſoule:</hi> For we are preſently as we depart hence, either in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, with poor <hi>Lazarus,</hi> or in hell torments, with the rich glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="part">
               <head>XCIX.</head>
               <p>I Read of one <hi>Eleazar</hi> the ſon of <hi>Hircanus,</hi> that being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, when it would be time to repent and amend? he anſwered, <hi>One day before death:</hi> and when the other replyed, <hi>that no man knew the day of his death,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>Begin then even to day, for fear of failing</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">Druſius in his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew and Arabian Apoph. Lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>. We have all often heard, no doubt, and therefore ſhould well know, though we often forget, and therefore are ſtill to learne; that
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:106771:93"/>our life is of ſuch uncertainty, that we are no ſooner borne, but we are in danger of death; one foot no ſooner on the ground, but the other ready to ſtep into the grave: the bud is ſometimes blaſted as well as the blowne roſe; the wind bloweth down the bloſſome as well as the fruit: yea we ſome of us confeſſe, with our lips at leaſt, that nothing is more certaine then the change of life, and nothing more uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine then the houre when it will change: the which for ought we know may be this houre; why then do we not this houre call our ſelves to account, &amp; amend our lives, leſt another houre be denied us, and death find us ſleeping in our accuſtomed wickedneſſe, and ſo the gate of mercy which is now open be ſhut up for ever?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="part">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:106771:93"/>
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GAſpar</hi> a man of no ſmall account in that Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilian Councell aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at <hi>Trent,</hi> being convicted and urged in his conſcience, for the Lawfulneſſe, and duty of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Sacrament in both kinds, according to the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of our Saviour Chriſt, and practice Eccleſiaſticall for more then a thouſand years, (for the Communion under one kind, was decreed firſt in the Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> 1414.) yet was ſtill obſtinately bent, to bar the people from the cup; and would not yeild to reſtore the uſe of it; <hi>leſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>we ſhould ſeeme to erre:</hi> They had grievouſly offended God, and groſſely wronged men by ſuch an impoſture, but yet he thought it leſſe damage to the offenders to ſtifle their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:106771:94"/>then to ſtaine their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits; Many wicked and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous opinions, which have ſince crept into the Church, might be, no doubt, eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and aboliſhed, but that the broachers and maintainers of them may not now entertaine the truth, leſt they be ſeene to have been deceived: that they thinke would be a great blemiſh in their Armes, a grievous disfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure in their faces, and not to be indured; and therefore, though they be ſanded and ſet on ground, yet they muſt needs keep up ſaile ſtill, as if they had water at their pleaſure. O this unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe of appearing to erre, holdeth men ſo in bondage to their errours, that it hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed many a ſoul; hath been the bane of thouſands and ten thouſands that had rather be damned then ſaved.</p>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:106771:94"/>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HIERON. ad PAULIN.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Eſſe Chriſtianum grande eſt, non videri, non vocari.</p>
                  <p>To be a Chriſtian, is a weighty matter, but not ſo to ſeeme, not ſo to be called.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LEO Epiſt. 83.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Eccleſiae nomine armamini, &amp; contra Eccleſiam dimicatis.</p>
                  <p>You are armed with the name of the Church, and you fight againſt the Church.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
